<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/users-and-groups/">
<chapter>
<title>Users and Groups</title>

<body>
<p>
If your ebuild requires a user or group to be added for a daemon, for example,
this should be performed via the functions available in <c>user.eclass</c>.
Regardless of whether you are adding a group or a user, this should be performed
in the <c>pkg_setup</c> phase function. <c>pkg_setup</c> is called
before the compile process, with
<uri link="::general-concepts/sandbox">sandbox</uri>
disabled, so a build that requires the user to exist will
have it, and is also called for both binary and source packages. You may also
use the <c>pkg_preinst</c> or <c>pkg_postinst</c> functions for user creation, if
the user is not required during or before <c>src_install</c>.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Adding Groups</title>
<body>

<p>
To add a group, use the <c>enewgroup</c> function:
</p>

<pre>
enewgroup &lt;name&gt; [gid]
</pre>

<p>
By default the next available group ID is selected. To set a specfic group ID,
pass it an extra argument to <c>enewgroup</c>.
</p>

<note>
Group IDs should rarely be hardcoded. If this is the case, you should
probably check first on gentoo-dev.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Adding Users</title>
<body>

<p>
To add a user, use the <c>enewuser</c> function:
</p>

<pre>
enewuser &lt;user&gt; [uid] [shell] [homedir] [groups]
</pre>

<p>
By default, both <c>enewuser</c> and <c>enewgroup</c> allocate the next available user
ID or group ID to the new user or group - if not, you explicitly have to specify
one.
</p>

<p>
Arguments for <c>enewuser</c> must be passed in the order as shown above: if you do
not want to specify a fixed user ID however but do want to set a specific shell,
for example, use <c>-1</c> for the <c>uid</c> parameter. The same applies for any other
parameter where you want to keep the default setting.
</p>

<p>
Groups for the <c>groups</c> argument should be separated by a comma (<c>,</c>) and
wrapped correctly, for example:
</p>

<pre>
enewuser frozd -1 -1 -1 "backup,frozd"
</pre>

<note>
User IDs should rarely be hardcoded. If this is the case, you should
probably check first on gentoo-dev.
</note>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
