<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/package-maintainers/">
<chapter>
<title>Package maintainers</title>
<body>

<p>
Package maintainers are responsible for ebuild maintenance tasks <d/>
bumping ebuilds to new upstream releases, updating them as necessary
with regards to policies, replying to bugs, etc. The maintainers
of a package are listed in the package's <uri
link="::ebuild-writing/misc-files/metadata/">metadata.xml</uri> file.
When assigning bugs, the first maintainer listed becomes the bug's
assignee and the remaining maintainers are added to CC, unless stated
otherwise in the metadata.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Maintainer authority</title>
<body>

<p>
Package maintainers have authority over their maintained packages.
Unless specified otherwise, you should request maintainers' approval
before committing to their packages. Try filing a bug, catching them
on IRC or sending a mail first. The exceptions to this rule are trivial
changes implied by your own actions, e.g. dependency updates as a result
of package moves.
</p>

<p>
In case of maintainer inactivity, it is a good idea to consult other
developers on how to handle the situation, especially if it is
a critical issue that needs to be handled ASAP. A customary tool
of maintainer timeout may be used in this case. This timeout can be
invoked if none of the package's maintainers reply to a patch within
2<d/>4 weeks of it being attached or linked to a correctly assigned bug,
or being sent to the maintainer.
</p>

<important>
Common sense dictates to us that toolchain/base-system/core packages
and eclasses or anything else which is delicate (e.g. glibc) or widely
used (e.g. GTK+) should usually be left to their maintainers.
If in doubt, don't touch it.
</important>

<p>
Respect developers' coding preferences. Unnecessarily changing
the syntax of an ebuild can cause complications for others. Syntax
changes should only be done if there is a real benefit, such as faster
compilation, improved information for the end user, or compliance
with Gentoo policies.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Adding and removing maintainers</title>
<body>

<p>
All packages newly added to the Gentoo repository must have at least
one maintainer specified. New maintainers can only be added with their
consent. In particular, it is not acceptable to add generic projects
(such as the Python project) as package maintainers without the approval
of their members or against their explicit policy.
</p>

<p>
Maintainers without commit access are called proxied maintainers. Their
changes must be pushed by a Gentoo developer, who acts as their proxy.
All packages maintained by proxied maintainers must explicitly list
their proxy developer or project in <c>metadata.xml</c>.
</p>

<p>
When adding new maintainers or removing old maintainers, please remember
to reassign bugs. The last maintainer to resign from maintaining
the package must place a <c>&lt;!-- maintainer-needed --&gt;</c> comment
in <c>metadata.xml</c>, in order simplify finding unmaintained packages.
It is also required to send an 'up for grabs' email to the
<c>gentoo-dev-announce</c> and <c>gentoo-dev</c> mailing lists,
providing a list of newly-unmaintained packages.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
