<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/filesystem/">
<chapter>
<title>Filesystem</title>

<body>
<p>
The basic filesystem layout and purpose is as follows:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>/bin</c>: Boot-critical applications</li>
  <li><c>/etc</c>: System administrator controlled configuration files</li>
  <li><c>/lib</c>: Boot-critical libraries</li>
  <li><c>/opt</c>: Binary-only applications.</li>
  <li><c>/sbin</c>: System administrator boot-critical applications</li>
  <li><c>/tmp</c>: Temporary data</li>
  <li><c>/usr</c>: General applications</li>
  <ul>
    <li><c>/usr/bin</c>: Applications</li>
    <li><c>/usr/lib</c>: Libraries</li>
    <li><c>/usr/local</c>: Non-portage applications. <b>Ebuilds must not install here</b>.</li>
    <li><c>/usr/sbin</c>: Non-system-critical system administrator applications</li>
    <li><c>/usr/share</c>: Architecture independent application data and documentation</li>
  </ul>
  <li><c>/var</c>: Program generated data</li>
  <ul>
    <li><c>/var/cache</c>: Long term data which can be regenerated</li>
    <li><c>/var/lib</c>: General application generated data</li>
    <li><c>/var/log</c>: Log files</li>
  </ul>
</ul>

<p>
Where possible, we prefer to put non-boot-critical applications in <c>/usr</c>
rather than <c>/</c>. If a program is not needed in the boot process until after
filesystems are mounted then it generally does not belong on <c>/</c>.
</p>

<p>
Any binary which links against a library under <c>/usr</c> must itself go into
<c>/usr</c> (or possibly <c>/opt</c>).
</p>

<p>
The <c>/opt</c> top-level should only be used for binary-only applications.
Binary-only applications must not be installed outside of <c>/opt</c>.
</p>

<p>
The <c>/usr/local</c> heirarchy is for non-portage software. Ebuilds must not
attempt to put anything in here.
</p>

<p>
The <c>/usr/share</c> directory is for <e>architecture independent</e> application data
which is not modified at runtime.
</p>

<p>
Try to avoid installing unnecessary things into <c>/etc</c> <d/> every file in there
is additional work for the system administrator. In particular, non-text files
and files that are not intended for system administrator usage should be moved
to <c>/usr/share</c>.
</p>

<section>
<title>FHS</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo does not consider the <uri link="http://www.pathname.com/fhs/">
Filesystem Hierarchy Standard</uri> to be an authoritative standard, although
much of our policy coincides with it.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
