<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/file-format/">
<chapter>
<title>Ebuild File Format</title>

<body>
<p>
An ebuild is a <c>bash</c> script which is executed within a special environment.
Files should be simple text files with a <c>.ebuild</c> extension.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>File Naming Rules</title>
<body>

<p>
An ebuild should be named in the form <c>name-version.ebuild</c>.
</p>

<p>
The name section should contain only lowercase non-accented letters, the digits
0-9, hyphens, underscores and plus characters. Uppercase characters are strongly
discouraged, but technically valid.
</p>

<note>
This is the same as <uri link="http://www.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/000095399/basedefs/xbd_chap03.html#tag_03_276">
IEEE1003.1-2004-3.276</uri>, with the exception of the period character and with the
addition of the plus character to keep GTK+ and friends happy.
</note>

<p>
The version section is more complicated. It consists of one or more numbers
separated by full stop (or period, or dot, or decimal point) characters (eg
<c>1.2.3</c>, <c>20050108</c>). The final number may have a single letter following it
(e.g. <c>1.2b</c>). This letter should not be used to indicate 'beta' status <d/>
portage treats <c>1.2b</c> as being a later version than <c>1.2</c> or <c>1.2a</c>.
</p>

<p>
There can be a suffix to version indicating the kind of release. In the following table,
what portage considers to be the 'lowest' version comes first.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Suffix</th>
    <th>Meaning</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>_alpha</c></ti>
    <ti>Alpha release (earliest)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>_beta</c></ti>
    <ti>Beta release</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>_pre</c></ti>
    <ti>Pre release</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>_rc</c></ti>
    <ti>Release candidate</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>(no suffix)</ti>
    <ti>Normal release</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>_p</ti>
    <ti>Patch level</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Any of these suffixes may be followed by a non-zero positive integer.
</p>

<p>
These suffixes can be chained together and will be processed iteratively.  To
give some examples (the following list is from lowest version to highest):

<ul>
  <li>foo-1.0.0_alpha_rc1</li>
  <li>foo-1.0.0_alpha_pre</li>
  <li>foo-1.0.0_beta_pre</li>
  <li>foo-1.0.0_beta_p1</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
Finally, version may have a Gentoo revision number in the form <c>-r1</c>. The initial
Gentoo version should have no revision suffix, the first revision should be
<c>-r1</c>, the second <c>-r2</c> and so on. See <uri link="::general-concepts/ebuild-revisions"/>.
</p>

<p>
Overall, this gives us a filename like <c>libfoo-1.2.5b_pre5-r2.ebuild</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Ebuild Header</title>
<body>

<p>
All ebuilds committed to the tree should have a three line header immediately at
the start indicating copyright. This must be an exact copy of the contents of
<c>$(portageq portdir)/header.txt</c>. Ensure that the <c>$Header: $</c> line is not
modified manually <d/> CVS will handle this line specially.
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
# Copyright 1999-2006 Gentoo Foundation
# Distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License v2
# $Header: $
</codesample>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Indenting and Whitespace</title>
<body>

<p>
Indenting in ebuilds must be done with tabs, one tab per indent
level. Each tab represents four spaces. Tabs should only be used for
indenting, never inside strings.
</p>

<p>
Avoid trailing whitespace: repoman will warn you about this if your
ebuild contains trailing or leading whitespace (whitespace instead of
tabs for indentation) when you commit.
</p>

<p>
Where possible, try to keep lines no wider than 80 positions. A
'position' is generally the same as a character <d/> tabs are four
positions wide, and multibyte characters are just one position wide.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Character Set</title>
<body>
<p>
All ebuilds (and eclasses, metadata files and ChangeLogs) must use the
UTF-8 character set. See <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0031.html">GLEP 31</uri>
for details.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
