<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/copyright-policy/">
<chapter>
<title>Copyright policy</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/glep/glep-0076.html">GLEP 76</uri> defines
copyright and license policies for Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
Every Gentoo project must abide by the
<uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/get-started/philosophy/social-contract.html">
Gentoo Social Contract</uri> and release its work under one or more of the
following licenses:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <uri link="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.html">
    GNU General Public License, version 2 or later</uri> (GPL-2+)
  </li>
  <li>
    The <uri link="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
    Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</uri>
    (CC-BY-SA-4.0), only for documentation
  </li>
  <li>
    Any
    <uri link="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.en.html#GPLCompatibleLicenses">
    GPL-compatible free software license</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Exceptions for other (GPL-incompatible) free software licenses may be granted
by the Gentoo Foundation on a case-by-case basis.
</p>

</body>

<section>
<title>Certificate of Origin</title>
<body>

<p>
Per GLEP 76, you must sign-off all your commits to any Gentoo-hosted repository
with accordance to the
<uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/glep/glep-0076.html#certificate-of-origin">
copyright policy</uri>.
</p>

<p>
When committing work authored by someone else, e.g. a Bugzilla patch, or GitHub
pull request, a sign-off from the original author is always strongly
recommended, in order to indicate that the author acknowledges Gentoo's
copyright policy. However, it is not mandatory for every case. Please refer to
the example list below when determining whether a sign-off from the original
author is, or is not required. The list below serves as a general guideline.
</p>
</body>

<subsection>
<title>General guideline</title>
<body>

<figure link="diagram.png" short="When can a contribution be accepted?"
        caption="Flowchart showing the steps for accepting a contribution" />

<p>
When can a contribution be accepted?
</p>

<ol type="1">
  <li>
    <p>
    When signed off by its author (i.e. with a <c>Signed-off-by</c> line):
    </p>
    <p>
    Can be accepted, because the author has confirmed that it is under a free
    software license. The committer adds another <c>Signed-off-by</c> line and
    certifies the commit under point 4 of the
    <uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/glep/glep-0076.html#certificate-of-origin">
    Certificate of Origin</uri>.
    </p>
    <note>
    Use common sense here, especially if you don't know the contributor.
    If the contribution was taken from somewhere else and the contributor
    doesn't have the right to distribute it under a free software license,
    you as the committer might get into trouble. So in this situation, do your
    best to check repositories for matching code, and whether they hold any
    special copyright claims.
    </note>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
    When <e>not</e> signed off:
    </p>
    <ol type="a">
      <li>
        <p>
        If the contribution is not of
        <uri link="https://www.gnu.org/prep/maintain/html_node/Legally-Significant.html">
        "legally significant"</uri> size (by the FSF's 15-lines rule of thumb):
        </p>
        <p>
        Can be accepted. The committer adds a <c>Signed-off-by</c> line and
        certifies the commit under point 2 of the Certificate of Origin.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        If the contribution is of significant size, and
        </p>
        <ol type="i">
          <li>
            <p>
            with an independent indication of its license (e.g. copyright and
            license notices in the file's header):
            </p>
            <p>
            Can be accepted. The committer adds a <c>Signed-off-by</c> line and
            certifies the commit under point 2 of the Certificate of Origin.
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
            <e>without</e> any other indication of its license:
            </p>
            <p>
            Can <e>not</e> be accepted. There's no indication that the author
            has released their work under a free license, therefore it must not
            be distributed by Gentoo.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>
</body>
</subsection>

</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
