<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/ebuild-maintenance/">
<chapter>
<title>Ebuild Maintenance</title>

<body>
<p>
This guide aims to explain common everyday ebuild maintenance
routines, as well as other rarer maintenance routines which
developers may not be familiar with.
</p>

<section>
<title>Adding a new ebuild</title>
<body>

<subsection>
<title>What (not) to put in the Portage tree</title>
<body>

<p>
Before writing a new ebuild, check 
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> 
to see if an ebuild has already been written for the package, but has not yet 
been added to the Portage tree.  Go to <uri 
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, choose query and select 
Advanced Search; as product select <e>Gentoo Linux</e>, as component select 
<e>ebuilds</e>.  In the search field put the name of the ebuild and as status 
select NEW, ASSIGNED, REOPENED and RESOLVED (RESOLVED is important), then 
submit the query.  For you lazy people, click <uri 
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/query.cgi?product=Gentoo%20Linux&amp;component=Ebuilds&amp;bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED">here</uri>.
</p>

<p>
In general, the Portage tree should only be used for storing 
<path>.ebuild</path> files, as well as any relatively small companion
files, such as patches or sample configuration files.  These types of
files should be placed in the <path>/usr/portage/mycat/mypkg/files</path>
directory to keep the main <path>mycat/mypkg</path> directory uncluttered.
Exceptions to this rule are for larger patch files (we recommend this for patches
above 20KB) which should be put onto the Gentoo mirrors so that people
do not waste excessive amounts of bandwidth and hard drive
space. Also, you should not add binary (non-ASCII) files to the
Portage CVS tree. If you need to do this in another CVS tree, for
example, if you need to add a small PNG graphic for whatever reason,
be sure to add it to CVS by using the <c>-kb</c> option, like so:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding binary files to CVS">
# <i>cvs add -kb myphoto.png</i>
</pre>

<p>
The <c>-kb</c> option tells CVS that <path>myphoto.png</path> is a binary
file and should be treated specially.  For example, merging the 
differences between two different versions of this file should not be 
allowed to happen, for obvious reasons.  Also, speaking of merging 
changes, any patches you add to Portage should generally <e>not</e> be 
compressed.  This will allow CVS to merge changes and correctly inform 
developers of conflicts.
</p>

<p>
Remember, the packages that you commit must be <e>ready</e> <e>out of the 
box</e> for end users when committed as stable.  Make sure that you have a good 
set of default settings that will satisfy the majority of systems and 
users that will use your package.  If your package is broken, and you are 
not sure how to get it to work, check some other distributions that have 
done their own versions of the package.  You can check 
<uri link="http://cvs.mandriva.com/cgi-bin/viewvc.cgi/SPECS/">Mandriva</uri>
or <uri link="http://www.debian.org/distrib/packages">Debian</uri> or 
<uri link="http://cvs.fedora.redhat.com/">Fedora</uri> for some 
examples.
</p>

<p>
When committing to CVS, all developers should use <c>repoman commit</c> 
instead of <c>cvs commit</c> to submit their ebuilds.  Before committing, 
please run <c>repoman full</c> to make sure you didn't forget something.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Initial Architecture Keywords</title>
<body>
<p>
When adding a new ebuild, you should only include <c>KEYWORDS</c> for
architectures on which you have actually tested the ebuild, confirming
that it works as it should and that <c>USE</c> flags are properly
honoured in the resulting package which would be installed. If
possible, you should give the actual library or application thorough
testing as well, since you would be responsible for any breakages for
your architecture(s). Minimal testing such as checking that the
application starts up without any errors should always be performed.
</p>

<p>
If you are adding a user-submitted ebuild, do not assume that the
submitter has done testing on various architectures: often, <c>KEYWORDS</c>
are cloned across packages or generated from documentation in the
source packages, which does not signify that the package does indeed
work on those architectures.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>CVS Commit Policy</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li>Always run <c>repoman scan</c> before you commit.</li>
<li>Please run <c>repoman full</c> before you commit.</li>
<li>Always test that <path>package.mask</path> is okay by doing 
<c>emerge --pretend mypkg</c> before you commit and check 
that it doesn't contain any conflicts.</li>
<li>Always update the <path>ChangeLog</path> before you commit.</li>
<li>Always commit the updated <path>package.mask</path> before 
the updated package, in case conflicts occur while you commit 
<path>package.mask</path>.</li>
<li>Always do atomic commits; if you commit a package with a new license, 
or that is masked, then first commit the revised <path>package.mask</path> and/or license, 
then commit the ebuild, <path>ChangeLog</path>, patches
and <uri link="::ebuild-writing/misc-files/metadata">metadata.xml</uri> all in <b>one</b> go
to avoid breaking users' installations.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>The files Directory</title>
<body>

<p>
As noted earlier, under each package subdirectory is
a <path>files/</path> directory. Any patches, configuration files, or
other ancillary files your package might require should be added to
this directory; any files bigger than 20KB-or-so should go to the
mirrors to lower the amount of (unneeded) files our users have to
download. You may want to consider naming patches you create yourself
just to get your package to build with a version-specific name, such
as <path>mypkg-1.0-gentoo.diff</path>, or more
simply, <path>1.0-gentoo.diff</path>.  Also note that the
<path>gentoo</path> extension informs people that this patch was created 
by us, the Gentoo Linux developers, rather than having been grabbed from a 
mailing list or somewhere else. Again, you should not compress these 
patches because CVS does not play well with binary files.
</p>

<p>
Consider prefixing or suffixing (such as <path>mypkg-1.0</path>) every file 
you put into the <path>files/</path> directory, so that the files used for 
each individual version on an ebuild are distinguishable from one another, and 
so that the changes between different revisions are visible.  This is generally 
a really good idea :).  You may want to use a different suffix if you wish to 
convey more meaning with the patch name.
</p>

<p>
If you have many files that should go into the <path>files/</path> directory, 
consider creating subdirectories such as <path>files/1.0/</path> and putting the
relevant files in the appropriate subdirectory.  If you use this method, 
you do not need to add version information to the names of the files, 
which is often more convenient.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Stabilizing ebuilds</title>
<body>

<p>
Only architecture maintainers for a given architecture should mark packages as 
stable on that architecture. The maintainer of the package should always be 
contacted just in case there are reasons not to do so. The exception to this 
is if you are part of an architecture team, in which case you may mark the 
package stable for that architecture. If you are not part of an architecture 
team, you should consult the guidelines below; if the architecture you are 
looking for is not listed then please consult the relevant lead.
</p>

<p>
You should <e>never</e> stabilize packages on
architectures for which you cannot test and instead you should file a bug to
the relevant architecture team, such as <mail link="sparc@gentoo.org">
sparc@gentoo.org</mail> asking them to stabilize the
ebuild. Alternatively, you may be able to find Gentoo developers on
IRC who could help you with your request.
</p>

<p>
It is best to not use <mail link="arch-maintainers@gentoo.org">
arch-maintainers@gentoo.org</mail>, adding architecture teams onto a
bug's CC list individually instead. That way teams can remove
themselves from the list when they are done, giving a clear indication
of which teams still have to stabilize a package.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Stabilization rules</title>
<body>

<p>
SPARC: You must have prior permission from the arch lead. Usually we expect
you to be on the sparc alias for QA reasons, although other arrangements
can be made if you will only be working with a small group of packages.
</p>

<p>
ALPHA: Maintainers may keyword their own packages but are reminded to inform
the Alpha team if they can help out with testing and keywording packages so
the team can keep an eye out for possible keywording mistakes.
</p>

<p>
Exotic architectures (like alpha, ia64, s390, sh, sparc, hppa, ppc*) are short on manpower, so it's best if you avoid opening stabilization bugs for them unless it is absolutely necessary (eg, a reverse dependency for your package). More about keywording policies can be found in the <uri link="::keywording">keywording</uri> section.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Upgrading ebuilds</title>
<body>

<p>
New ebuilds should rarely go in with "<c>arch</c>" keywords and even if they do
not, the package <e>must</e> be tested on any architectures listed in the
<c>KEYWORDS</c> variable of the new ebuild.
</p>

<p>
Exceptions to the no "<c>arch</c>" rule are major bug fixes, or
security fixes. If the previous version of the ebuild
contains <c>KEYWORDS</c> which you cannot test for, you should
downgrade them: turn any "<c>arch</c>" keyword to "<c>~arch</c>". If you
think that your package may not work at all even on "<c>~arch</c>"
then it is best to leave the keyword out and request testing from the
relevant team: if you are to do this, you must file a bug to the team
in question.
</p>

<p>
If a new version introduces new dependencies which are not available
on some architectures, then you should file a bug or ask on IRC before
you upgrade the package. If you really need to get the ebuild added in
a hurry, for example, for a security fix, then you should drop
any <c>KEYWORDS</c> which are causing problems and CC the relevant
architectures on the bug - you should file a new bug to the
architecture in question regarding this if no bug is already
available.
</p>

<p>
If there are no new dependencies, do not remove keywords if your
commit fails with repoman - please try a full <c>cvs update</c> and if
you still have problems, then commit with <c>repoman -I</c> and file a
bug to the broken architecture, noting it in your CVS commit message.
</p>

<warn>
When committing, make sure that you reference any bugs in the
ChangeLog as well as the CVS message. Failing to do so is considered
to be in very poor taste and may result in disciplinary action.
</warn>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Moving ebuilds</title>
<body>

<p>
Moving ebuilds is a two-step process:
</p>

<p>
Firstly, you need to move the ebuild in CVS. To do this, you should
copy the ebuild to its new location and commit that as you would with
a <uri link="#adding-a-new-ebuild">new ebuild</uri>.
</p>

<p>
After this, you should change any ebuilds which <c>DEPEND</c> on the
old ebuild to depend on the new one. After this, should add an entry to the
latest file in <path>profiles/updates/</path> in the Portage tree in the in
the following format:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding an entry to updates">
move net-misc/fwbuilder net-firewall/fwbuilder
</pre>

<p>
This example would transparently move <path>net-misc/fwbuilder</path> to
<path>net-firewall/fwbuilder</path> if users have it installed. This
way, users would now automatically receive updates
for <path>net-firewall/fwbuilder</path> when they are available.
</p>

<p>
Once this step is concluded, you are allowed to remove the old package.
Simply issue a <c>cvs remove -Rf $PN</c> in the package category and commit
the changes afterwards with a meaningful commit message. Don't forget to update
entries in files such as profiles/package.mask to reflect the new category. Finally
remember to change the title to open bugs related to this package if needed.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing a package">
net-misc # cvs rm -Rf fwbuilder
cvs remove: use `cvs commit' to remove these files permanently
net-misc # cvs ci -m "Moving net-misc/fwbuilder to net-firewall/fwbuilder."
</pre>

<note>
CVS cannot destroy directories: it will simply not re-create them if
they are blank, providing you use CVS with the <c>-P</c> flag.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Changing ebuild's SLOT</title>
<body>
<p>
The process for changing the ebuild's SLOT is very similar to the previous process.
Besides changing the SLOT in the ebuild file, you also need to create a new entry
in <path>profiles/updates/</path> in the Portage tree in the following format:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding an entry to updates">
slotmove app-text/gtkspell 0 2
</pre>

<p>Make sure that you have fixed all the reverse dependencies and that you have
updated every file in <path>profiles/</path> directory that happens to contain an
entry which may be affected by your change.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Removing ebuilds</title>
<body>

<p>
When removing an ebuild make sure that no dependencies in Portage are broken
due to the removal - additionally, your CVS commit message should explain
clearly why the ebuild is being removed from CVS.
</p>

<p>
If you need to remove ebuilds, make sure you do not accidentally remove
the newest/only stable ebuild for any architecture. If you would like to
get a newer version marked stable, then please file a bug or ask on IRC.
</p>

<p>
You should also not cause an unnecessary downgrade for any "<c>~arch</c>"
when removing ebuilds - instead, it is best to get the newest version
marked "<c>~arch</c>" first and then remove redundant versions of the ebuild.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Removing a package</title>
<body>

<p>
When removing packages follow these steps:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>Make sure that no dependencies in Portage are broken due to the removal</li>
  <li>Send last rites to gentoo-dev-announce and gentoo-dev</li>
  <li>Mask the package</li>
  <li>Wait 30 days (or more)</li>
  <li>Remove from CVS unless the reason for removal has been fixed</li>
  <li>Remove package.mask entry</li>
  <li>Close open bugs as WONTFIX</li>
</ol> 

<p>
In order to remove a package completely from CVS, delete any files from the
directory and commit this, CVS will take care of removing empty directories
itself.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing a package from CVS"><comment>#</comment> <keyword>cd</keyword> app-admin
<comment>#</comment> <keyword>cvs</keyword> rm -Rf scotty
<comment>#</comment> <keyword>cvs</keyword> ci -m "app-admin/scotty removal (pending 21st July 2006), see #77501 for reference." scotty</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Conflicting files</title>
<body>

<p>
When you encounter a package that is trying to install files that are
already provided by another package (detectable with
<c>FEATURES=collision-protect</c> for example) you have to fix this
situation before you can commit the ebuild or, if you encounter this
with an existing package, file a bug about that package (see below for
a few exceptions). The reason file conflicts are critical is because
if "foo" provides the file <path>/usr/bin/example</path> and "bar" is
going to overwrite it, and later "bar" is unmerged, Portage will remove
<path>/usr/bin/example</path> and it is therefore likely it will break
"foo".
</p>

<p>
The most obvious fix is to add a blocking dependency to both packages
that want to install that file, so they can't be installed at the same
time. But unless there are also other reasons for those packages to
block each other you should avoid this if possible and rather fix the
package, which could include one or more of the following steps:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Make "foo" (R)DEPEND on "bar" and not install the conflicting 
  file.</li>
  <li>Remove conflicting files from "foo" in <c>src_install</c>
  or <c>pkg_preinst</c>.</li>
  <li>Move conflicting files into a new subpackage and make "foo" and
  "bar" both (R)DEPEND on that package.</li>
  <li>Change the location where "foo" or "bar" installs conflicting
  files.</li>
</ul>

<p>
In some cases conflicting files can't be really fixed or aren't
critical, currently known exceptions are Perl module manpages
(overwriting the ones from Perl itself) and <c>CONFIG_PROTECT</c>'ed
files (which should still be fixed, but aren't critical as Portage
won't overwrite them).
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
