<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/misc-files/patches/">
<chapter>
<title>Patches</title>

<body>
<p>
There is no fixed rule for patch naming. The following are guidelines
only.
</p>

<p>
Small patches (less than, say, a few KBytes) should be added to
<c>${FILESDIR}</c>. If you anticipate having several patches, it often
helps to create version numbered subdirectories <d/> <c>${FILESDIR}/${PV}/</c>
is conventional. Patches are best named <c>${P}-what-it-does.patch</c> (or
<c>.diff</c>), where <c>what-it-does</c> is a two or three word
description of what the patch is for. If the patch is to fix a
specific bug, it is often useful to add in the bug number <d/> for
example, <c>vim-7.0-cron-vars-79981.patch</c>. If the patch is pulled from
upstream's VCS repository, it can help to include the revision
number in the patch name as a suffix to the version part <d/>
<c>fluxbox-0.9.12-3860-menu-backups.patch</c>.
</p>

<p>
Larger patches should be
<uri link="::general-concepts/mirrors/#Suitable Download Hosts">
mirrored</uri>, preferably on the Gentoo Infrastructure. When
mirroring patches, choosing a name that will not cause conflicts is
important — the <c>${P}</c> prefix is highly recommended
here. Mirrored patches are often compressed with <c>xz</c> or
<c>bzip2</c>. Remember to list these patches in <c>SRC_URI</c>.
</p>

<note>
Patches included in <c>${FILESDIR}</c> should never be compressed.
</note>

<warning>
Starting from EAPI=6 a strip patch level was limited to the <c>-p1</c>.
Although it can be overridden with a <c>eapply -p&lt;strip_level&gt;</c>
command, it is higly recommended to adapt the patch itself to work
with the <c>-p1</c> default.
</warning>

<p>
If a package requires many patches, even if they are individually
small, it is often best to create a patch tarball to avoid cluttering
up the tree too much.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Patch Descriptions</title>
<body>
<p>
It is possible to include a description with a patch. This is often
helpful when others come to work with your packages, or, indeed when
you come back to take a look at your own package a few months
later. Good things to include in comments are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    What the patch actually does. Bug numbers are good here.
  </li>
  <li>
    Where the patch came from. Is it an upstream VCS pull,
    something from Bugzilla, something you wrote?
  </li>
  <li>
    Whether the patch has been sent upstream, if applicable.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
To include the description, simply insert it at the top of the patch
file. The <c>patch</c> tool will ignore leading text until it finds
something that looks like it might be a 'start patching' instruction,
so as long as each description line starts with letters (rather than
numbers, symbols or whitespace) there shouldn't be a
problem. Alternatively, prefix each description line with a hash
(that's <c>#</c>, or 'pound' to the USians) sign. It's also best to
leave a single blank line after the description and before the main
patch.
</p>

<p>
Here's a simple example (<c>023_all_vim-6.3-apache-83565.patch</c>)
from the <c>vim</c> patch tarball:
</p>

<pre>
# Detect Gentoo apache files properly. Gentoo bug 83565.

--- runtime/filetype.vim.orig   2005-03-25 01:44:12.000000000 +0000
+++ runtime/filetype.vim        2005-03-25 01:45:15.000000000 +0000
@@ -93,6 +93,9 @@
 " Gentoo apache config file locations (Gentoo bug #76713)
 au BufNewFile,BufRead /etc/apache2/conf/*/* setf apache

+" More Gentoo apache config file locations (Gentoo bug #83565)
+au BufNewFile,BufRead /etc/apache2/{modules,vhosts}.d/*.conf setf apache
+
 " XA65 MOS6510 cross assembler
 au BufNewFile,BufRead *.a65                    setf a65
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Clean Patch Howto</title>
<body>

<pre>
---------------------
  CLEAN PATCH HOWTO
---------------------

when i say "clean patch", i am not referring to the patch itself (as in the
changes it makes to the source code).  i am referring to all the metadata that
exists in the patch to make it "maintainable".

-------
  WHY
-------

you might be thinking "wow, this looks like effort".  well you best shut your
brain hole and do it anyways.  seriously though ...

this may take more effort "up front", but the amount of effort that it saves
for everyone else in the future more than makes up for it.  i refer to other
distributions or upstream maintainers that read the patch.  or future Gentoo
maintainers / developers.  too many hours have i spent staring at a patch
(whether it be long or tiny) with no documentation and no references as to why
the changes it is making to a package exist at all.  by keeping all patches
"clean", people can quickly and easily assess a patch without searching through
a metric butt ton of other files.

so make your patch clean in the first place and stop screwing others in ways
they do not enjoy.  stick with the pleasant methods please.

---------------
  FILE NAMING
---------------

this is quick to do, so let's get it out of the way.  your patch name should be
short and to the point.  when doing a file listing (e.g. `ls files/`), it's a
lot easier to be able to scan for relevant patches when they have good keywords
in their file names.

it should also include the package name and the version it was written against.
this way people searching for patches or who happen to just stumble across the
file itself have a clue as to what it's for.  stripping out the $PN (and to a
lesser extent, the $PV) makes the filename significantly less useful.  the fact
the files are typically stored in $CATEGORY/$PN/files/ is irrelevant.  we're
trying to think beyond the Gentoo box here.

it's also more consistent.  consistency matters as minor/pointless deviations
only serve to slow people down.

-------
  HOW
-------

here's a check list of things to keep in the patch header:
 - external references
	- upstream mailing archives
	- upstream bug reports
	- upstream commit links
	- upstream changelog entries
	- Gentoo bug reports
 - short / medium explanation
	- why is the patch needed ?
	- what is it fixing ?
	- why is it fixing it the way it is ?
	- proposal for better fixes in the future ?
	- is it a stop gap measure (workaround) ?
	- how was it regression tested ?
	- examples of before / after behavior
		- how to reproduce bug w/out patch
		- how to show bug is fixed after patch
		- maybe upstream fixed it in a different way, so this test can be
		  used to show that the patch is no longer needed w/newer versions
 - status
	- was it merged/rejected/postponed/etc... upstream ?
	- is it distribution-specific ?
 - attribution
	- who found the bug ?
	- who fixed the bug ?
	- who wrote the patch ?
	- who tested the patch ?
	- who gave advice on the patch ?

all this information should be *in the patch itself*.  it should never ever be
found in something like the ebuild.  if you really really want to put a comment
next to a patch in an ebuild, then this is about the only thing that is OK:
	epatch "${FILESDIR}"/${P}-fatty-cow.patch #12345
(where 12345 is the Gentoo bug #)

when documenting these things, it might be useful to use RFC822/git style tags
to format the metadata.  so when documenting the author, use:
	From: Nice Person &lt;foo@cow.com&gt;
or when documenting relevant urls, use something like:
	Project-Bug-URL: http://upstream.tracker.com/12345
	Gentoo-Bug-URL: http://bugs.gentoo.org/9889
and if you want to note your approval, slap on a s-o-b tag:
	Signed-off-by: Diligent Developer &lt;funky-cow-butt@gentoo.org&gt;

finally, your patch should be clear of useless cruft.  if it was not taken
straight from an upstream SCM (`git format-patch` or `svn diff -r #` or
`cvs diff -r 1.123 -r 1.124`), then the metadata is useless.  so delete it.
i'm referring to things like the diff command used to produce the patch, or the
timestamps on the files, local revision info, or other similar spam. note that
the context info (the stuff that comes after the @@) should be left as that can
be invaluable when applying patches to later versions.  for example:
@@ -80,6 +82,7 @@ case $sys in
                  ^^^^^^^^^^^^ keep this part
extra points if you make the filename in the ---/+++ section consistent and
sane.  i.e. remove different leading backup/paths/ and .orig/.new suffixes.
extra extra points if your patch is in the -p1 format.  this tends to be much
more standard than any other -p#.  a good suggestion is to use the package
name / version as the leading portion that gets stripped.

also note that while `patch` uses the timestamp info in order to remove empty
files automatically, in Gentoo, we apply all patches with -E, so the timestamp
info does not matter.  if you really want to keep an empty file around though,
just replace the file with a comment or an empty line or ...

if deleting these things yourself sounds like the kind of fun that involves
nipple clamps and electricity, try this:
scrub_patch() {
	sed -i \
		-e '/^index /d' \
		-e '/^new file mode /d' \
		-e '/^Index:/d' \
		-e '/^=========/d' \
		-e '/^RCS file:/d' \
		-e '/^retrieving/d' \
		-e '/^diff/d' \
		-e '/^Files .* differ$/d' \
		-e '/^Only in /d' \
		-e '/^Common subdirectories/d' \
		-e '/^deleted file mode [0-9]*$/d' \
		-e '/^+++/s:\t.*::' \
		-e '/^---/s:\t.*::' \
		"$@"
}
scrub_patch some-patch-you-found.patch

some more info can be found here:
http://devmanual.gentoo.org/ebuild-writing/misc-files/patches/index.html

-----------
  EXAMPLE
-----------

here we see a simple explanation and a URL for more info (this patch could do
with some attribution however ...).  no metadata exists from running the `diff`
command (timestamps, etc...).
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; man-1.6d-fbsd.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;
Fixes compilation in FreeBSD.

http://bugs.gentoo.org/138123

--- man-1.6d/gencat/genlib.c
+++ man-1.6d/gencat/genlib.c
@@ -54,7 +54,7 @@
 #include &lt;unistd.h&gt;
 #endif

-#ifndef __linux__
+#if !defined(__linux__) &amp;&amp; !defined(__FreeBSD__)
 #include &lt;memory.h&gt;
 static int bcopy(src, dst, length)
 char *src, *dst;

&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; man-1.6d-fbsd.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;


&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; util-linux-2.12q-dont-umask.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;
Don't force umask to 022 or the -o umask option doesn't work.

Patch by Daniel Drake.

https://bugs.gentoo.org/93671

--- mount/mount.c
+++ mount/mount.c
@@ -1491,8 +1491,6 @@ main(int argc, char *argv[]) {
    if ((p = strrchr(progname, '/')) != NULL)
        progname = p+1;

-   umask(022);
-
    /* People report that a mount called from init without console
       writes error messages to /etc/mtab
       Let us try to avoid getting fd's 0,1,2 */
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; util-linux-2.12q-dont-umask.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;


&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; iproute2-2.6.25.20080417-build.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;
Don't let target flags bleed into build flags.

Fix by Bertrand Jacquin.

https://bugs.gentoo.org/226035

--- netem/Makefile
+++ netem/Makefile
@@ -2,6 +2,7 @@ DISTGEN = maketable normal pareto paretonormal
 DISTDATA = normal.dist pareto.dist paretonormal.dist experimental.dist

 HOSTCC ?= $(CC)
+CCOPTS  = $(CBUILD_CFLAGS)
 LDLIBS += -lm

 all: $(DISTGEN) $(DISTDATA)
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; iproute2-2.6.25.20080417-build.patch &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
