<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="ebuild-maintenance/new-ebuild/">
<chapter>
<title>Adding a new ebuild</title>

<section>
<title>What (not) to put in the Gentoo repository</title>
<body>

<p>
Before writing a new ebuild, check <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/">
bugs.gentoo.org</uri> to see if an ebuild has already been written for
the package, but has not yet been added to the Gentoo repository. Go to
<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, choose query and
select Advanced Search; as product select <e>Gentoo Linux</e>, as component
select <e>New packages</e>. In the search field put the name of the ebuild and
as status and resolution select all possible fields, then submit the query.
For you lazy people, here is a
<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/query.cgi?format=advanced&amp;product=Gentoo%20Linux&amp;component=New%20packages">
Bugzilla advanced search</uri> link.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo repository should only be used for storing <c>.ebuild</c> files,
as well as any small companion files, such as patches or sample configuration
files. These files should have a size of at most 20 KiB and must be placed
in the <c>mycat/mypkg/files</c> directory, which can be referenced as
<c>${FILESDIR}</c> from within ebuilds.
</p>

<p>
Larger patches should be placed in your developer space on <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>
instead of the tree, in order to minimize the repository size.
Non-developers such as proxied maintainers can host patches at some stable
location of their own <d/> there is no security issue here as the Manifest
will record patch checksums at the time of commit.
</p>

<p>
The files in the repository should be uncompressed plain text files, i.e.,
no binaries. This will allow the version control system to merge changes and
correctly inform developers of conflicts.
</p>

<p>
Remember, the packages that you commit must be <e>ready</e> <e>out of the
box</e> for end users when committed as stable.  Make sure that you have a good
set of default settings that will satisfy the majority of systems and
users that will use your package.  If your package is broken, and you are
not sure how to get it to work, check some other distributions that have
done their own versions of the package.  You can check
<uri link="https://www.debian.org/distrib/packages">Debian</uri> or
<uri link="https://src.fedoraproject.org/projects/rpms/*">Fedora</uri> for some
examples.
</p>

<p>
When committing to git, all developers should use <c>pkgdev commit</c> with
<c>pkgdev push</c> instead of <c>git commit</c> to submit their ebuilds.
Before committing, please run <c>pkgcheck scan --commits</c> to make sure you
didn't forget something.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Initial architecture keywords</title>
<body>

<p>
When adding a new ebuild, you should only include <c>KEYWORDS</c> for
architectures on which you have actually tested the ebuild, confirming
that it works as it should and that <c>USE</c> flags are properly
honoured in the resulting package which would be installed. If
possible, you should give the actual library or application thorough
testing as well, since you would be responsible for any breakages for
your architecture(s). Minimal testing such as checking that the
application starts up without any errors should always be performed.
</p>

<p>
If you are adding a user-submitted ebuild, do not assume that the
submitter has done testing on various architectures: often, <c>KEYWORDS</c>
are cloned across packages or generated from documentation in the
source packages, which does not signify that the package does indeed
work on those architectures.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>The files directory</title>
<body>

<p>
As noted earlier, under each package subdirectory is
a <c>files/</c> directory. Any patches, configuration files, or
other ancillary files your package might require should be added to
this directory; any files bigger than 20KB-or-so should go to the
mirrors to lower the amount of (unneeded) files our users have to
download. You may want to consider naming patches you create yourself
just to get your package to build with a version-specific name, such
as <c>mypkg-1.0-gentoo.patch</c>, or more
simply, <c>1.0-gentoo.patch</c>.  Also note that the
<c>gentoo</c> extension informs people that this patch was created
by us, the Gentoo Linux developers, rather than having been grabbed from a
mailing list or somewhere else. Again, you should not compress these
patches.
</p>

<p>
Consider prefixing or suffixing (such as <c>mypkg-1.0</c>) every file
you put into the <c>files/</c> directory, so that the files used for
each individual version on an ebuild are distinguishable from one another, and
so that the changes between different revisions are visible.  This is generally
a really good idea :).  You may want to use a different suffix if you wish to
convey more meaning with the patch name.
</p>

<p>
If you have many files that should go into the <c>files/</c> directory,
consider creating subdirectories such as <c>files/1.0/</c> and putting the
relevant files in the appropriate subdirectory.  If you use this method,
you do not need to add version information to the names of the files,
which is often more convenient.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
