<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/functions/src_compile/building/">
<chapter>
<title>Building a Package</title>

<body>
<p>
The <c>emake</c> function should be used to call <c>make</c>. This will ensure that
the user's <c>MAKEOPTS</c> are used correctly. The <c>emake</c> function passes on
any arguments provided, so it can be used to make non-default targets (<c>emake
extras</c>), for example. Occasionally you might encounter a screwy non-autotools
<c>Makefile</c> that explodes with <c>emake</c>, but this is rare.
</p>

<p>
Builds should be tested with various <c>-j</c> settings in <c>MAKEOPTS</c> to ensure
that the build parallelises properly. If a package does <e>not</e> parallelise
cleanly, it should be patched.
</p>

<p>
If patching <e>really</e> isn't an option, <c>emake -j1</c> should be
used. However, when doing this please remember that you are seriously
hurting build times for many non-x86 users in particular. Forcing
a <c>-j1</c> can increase build times from a few minutes to an hour on
some MIPS and SPARC systems.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Fixing Compiler Usage</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes a package will try to use a bizarre compiler, or will need to be told
which compiler to use. In these situations, the <c>tc-getCC()</c> function from
<c>toolchain-funcs.eclass</c> should be used. Other similar functions are available
<d/> these are documented in <c>man toolchain-funcs.eclass</c>.
</p>

<note>
It is <e>not</e> correct to use the <c>${CC}</c> variable for this purpose.
</note>

<p>
Sometimes a package will not use the user's <c>${CFLAGS}</c> or <c>${LDFLAGS}</c>.
This must be worked around, as sometimes these variables are used for specifying
critical ABI options. In these cases, the build scripts should be modified (for
example, with <c>sed</c>) to use <c>${CFLAGS}</c> or <c>${LDFLAGS}</c> correctly.
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
inherit flag-o-matic toolchain-funcs

src_compile() {
    # -Os not happy
    replace-flags -Os -O2

    # We have a weird build.sh to work with which ignores our
    # compiler preferences. yay!
    sed -i -e "s:cc -O2:$(tc-getCC) ${CFLAGS} ${LDFLAGS}:" build.sh \
        || die "sed fix failed. Uh-oh..."
    ./build.sh || die "Build failed!"
}
</codesample>

<note>
When using <c>sed</c> with <c>CFLAGS</c> or <c>LDFLAGS</c>, it is not safe to use
a comma or a slash as a delimiter. The recommended character is a colon.
</note>

<p>
Portage performs a QA check which verifies if LDFLAGS are respected. This QA check
is enabled only when <c>LDFLAGS</c> variable contains <c>-Wl,--hash-style=gnu</c>.
(This flag can be used only on systems which use <c>sys-libs/glibc</c> except for
machines with a MIPS CPU.)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
