<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="hosted-projects/">
<chapter>
<title>Hosted Projects</title>

<body>
<p>
The following guidelines have been proposed for hosted projects in an attempt to
prevent a repeat of the <c>genkernel</c> disaster.
</p>

<section>
<title>Documentation Requirement</title>
<body>

<p>
All hosted projects should have decent, up to date user and developer
documentation. This documentation must be available <e>before the first release</e>,
and not left as "something we'll do later (honest)".
</p>

<p>
Our documentation team are happy to help out with GuideXMLification, translation
etc. for the user documentation, but they <e>need</e> various things to do this:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Basic documentation to start with.
  </li>
  <li>
    Basic information on the project or tool, such as:
    <ul>
      <li>
        The goals
      </li>
      <li>
        The design specification
      </li>
      <li>
        An FAQ
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    To be informed of any updates, in advance if at all possible <d/> this is to
    avoid having out of date recommendations in the documentation.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Developer documentation is generally best left in the hands of the project
maintainers.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Portability</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo runs on a large number of architectures. This is one of our big
advantages over some other distributions. It is therefore important that any
tools are made with portability in mind, <e>even if you originally think that your
tool is only relevant for one arch</e>. It was this kind of assumption that meant
that <c>genkernel</c> had to be completely rewritten when it suddenly became
mandatory.
</p>

<p>
In practice, this means the following:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Using a portable programming language <d/> no Java or C# for any Gentoo tools.
    Bash, C and Python are good, especially since everyone already has those
    installed.
  </li>
  <li>
    Not making assumptions about the hardware or architecture. This covers various
    things, depending upon the tool <d/> simple examples include:
    <ul>
      <li>
        Not assuming that you are running on a 32bit little endian system.
      </li>
      <li>
        Not assuming that all computers have a VGA text console, or indeed any
        kind of graphics capability.
      </li>
      <li>
        Not assuming that all computers use DOS disclabels.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    Not relying too strongly upon particular implementations of various tools,
    except where it has been agreed that we will always use a particular
    implementation of said tool (it is safe to use <c>GNU sed</c> extensions, for
    example, but <e>not</e> <c>GNU find</c> extensions).
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Open / Free</title>
<body>

<p>
All hosted projects should use an appropriate open / free / libre license.
Typically this will be the GPL v2 for software, and the Creative Commons license
for documentation. However, reasonable exceptions can be made <d/> sometimes it
makes more sense to use the LGPL or a *BSD license, and for application-specific
projects going with the application's license may make more sense (the
<c>gentoo-syntax</c> package for <c>vim</c> uses the <c>vim</c> license, for example).
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Accessible</title>
<body>

<p>
Projects should be accessible to users with disabilities. Simple examples of how
to go about this include:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Not relying solely upon colour to convey information.
  </li>
  <li>
    Providing textual descriptions for any images.
  </li>
  <li>
    Providing clear captions for dialogs, buttons, form fields and so on.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Good places to look for further hints include:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gap">GNOME Accessibility
      Project</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.w3.org/WAI/Resources/#gl">W3C Web Accessibility
      Initiative Guidelines</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
