<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="appendices/editor-configuration/emacs/">
<chapter>
<title>Configuring <c>emacs</c> for UTF-8</title>
<body>

<p>
Emacs 21 has built-in Unicode support, and (fortunately) it supports
UTF-8 far better than UTF-16 and other variants. Some extensions to this
functionality are available in the package <c>app-emacs/mule-ucs</c>, although
this is not necessary (and I would not recommend it unless absolutely
necessary, as the potential for unexpected bugs or quirky behaviour is
increased).
</p>

<p>
In versions of Emacs below 21.3, and a non-UTF-8 locale is used when
opening a UTF-8 file, auto-detection of the character set is effectively
disabled and characters will be garbled. The UTF-8 character set can be
preferred with <c>M-x prefer-coding-system</c> and entering <c>utf-8</c> when
prompted. Otherwise, it is necessary to tell Emacs that a UTF-8 file is
being opened by prefixing the <c>C-x C-f</c> or <c>C-x C-v</c> command with
<c>C-x C-m c utf-8 RET</c>. As a diagnostic measure, the coding system currently
in use can be determined with <c>C-h C &lt;RET&gt;</c>.
</p>

<p>
Newer Emacs versions will autodetect the coding system for given text.
</p>

<p>
If it is desired to prefer UTF-8 to the regular character set,
the following can be used inside of the Emacs startup file:
</p>

<pre>
    (prefer-coding-system 'utf-8)
</pre>

<p>
For specifying coding system to use on a per-file basis, the
<c>modify-coding-system</c> function can be used.
</p>

<section>
<title>Further Reading</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/emacs.html#Recognize%20Coding">
    http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/emacs.html#Recognize%20Coding</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/emacs.html#Specify%20Coding">
    http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/emacs.html#Specify%20Coding</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.emacswiki.org/cgi-bin/wiki/UnicodeEncoding">
    http://www.emacswiki.org/cgi-bin/wiki/UnicodeEncoding</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://www.emacswiki.org/cgi-bin/wiki/ChangingEncodings">
    http://www.emacswiki.org/cgi-bin/wiki/ChangingEncodings</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
