<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/mailing-lists/">
<chapter>
<title>Mailing lists</title>
<body>

<p>
Mailing lists are the most important communication media in Gentoo.
They are used to announce events, discuss changes, review code.  Use
of mailing lists is explicitly required by some of the processes such
as package last rites.
</p>

<p>
The complete list of Gentoo mailing lists can be found in the
<uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/get-involved/mailing-lists/">mailing
list</uri> section of the Gentoo website.  All mailing lists are
archived.  The archives for the public lists can be found on
the <uri link="https://archives.gentoo.org/">mailing list archives</uri>
site.  The data from the non-public archives can be provided
by the Infrastructure team at the request of a developer.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Primary developer mailing lists</title>
<body>

<p>
There are five primary lists intended for Gentoo developers
(and contributors):
</p>

<ul>
  <li>gentoo-core — internal non-public Gentoo developer list</li>
  <li>gentoo-dev — public technical discussion list</li>
  <li>gentoo-dev-announce — developer announcement list</li>
  <li>gentoo-nfp — Gentoo Foundation discussion list</li>
  <li>gentoo-project — public non-technical discussion list</li>
</ul>

<p>
Most of the discussions take place on the gentoo-dev and gentoo-project
mailing lists.  Strictly technical topics (e.g. ebuild development,
system behavior) go into gentoo-dev, while non-technical topics
(e.g. organizational matters) go into gentoo-project.  Both lists are
public and open to everyone.  Developers are strongly encouraged
to follow these lists.
</p>

<p>
The gentoo-nfp list is used for affairs strictly related to the Gentoo
Foundation.  For example, this includes funding and legal affairs.
</p>

<p>
The gentoo-dev-announce is used for important announcements that affect
developers, for example major policy changes, project news.  This list
is also used to announce last rites and packages needing new
maintainers.  gentoo-dev-announce is not meant to accept replies, so
all messages sent to it must be cross-posted to another mailing list
and have their Reply-To header set to that list.  Messages without Reply-To
are rejected, the remaining messages are moderated to prevent accidental
replies from coming through.
</p>

<p>
The gentoo-core mailing list is restricted to developers.
It is generally used when developers wish to share information regarding
their personal situation with other developers and to discuss sensitive
matters that cannot be published at the time.  The list is non-public
and it is forbidden to publicly discuss messages from -core, forward
them or cross-post to another mailing list.  All developers are
subscribed to it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
