<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/dependencies/">
<chapter>
<title>Dependencies</title>

<body>

<p>
  Automatic dependency resolution is one of the most useful features provided by
  <c>emerge</c>.
</p>

<section>
<title>Build Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>DEPEND</c> ebuild variable should specify any dependencies which are
required to unpack, patch, compile or install the package (but see
<uri link="::general-concepts/dependencies#Implicit System Dependency"/> for
exemptions).
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Runtime Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>RDEPEND</c> ebuild variable should specify any dependencies which are
required at runtime. This includes libraries (when dynamically linked), any data
packages and (for interpreted languages) the relevant interpreter. In EAPI=3 or
older, if this variable is not specified it defaults to the value of
<c>DEPEND</c>, however the implicit usage is frowned upon. In EAPI=4, the
implicit behaviour was removed and the assignment is always explicit.
</p>

<p>
Note that when installing from a binary package, only <c>RDEPEND</c> will be
checked. It is therefore necessary to include items even if they are also listed
in <c>DEPEND</c>.
</p>

<p>
Items which are in <c>RDEPEND</c> but not <c>DEPEND</c> could <e>in theory</e> be merged
<e>after</e> the target package. Portage does not currently do this.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Post-Merge Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>PDEPEND</c> variable specifies dependencies which must be merged <e>after</e> the
package. This is sometimes used for plugins which have a dependency upon the
package being merged. Generally <c>PDEPEND</c> should be avoided in favour of
<c>RDEPEND</c> except where this will create circular dependency chains.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Implicit System Dependency</title>
<body>

<p>
All packages have an implicit compile-time and runtime dependency upon the
entire <c>system</c> target. It is therefore not necessary, nor advisable, to
specify dependencies upon toolchain packages like <c>gcc</c>, <c>libc</c> and
so on, except where specific versions or packages (for example, <c>glibc</c>
over <c>uclibc</c>) are required.  Note that this rule also needs consideration
for packages like <c>flex</c>, <c>zlib</c> and <c>libtool</c>, which aren't in
the <c>system</c> target for every profile.  For example, the embedded profile
doesn't have <c>zlib</c> in <c>system</c> target, the <c>libtool</c> ABI might
change and break building order and <c>flex</c> might get removed from the
<c>system</c> target in future.
</p>

<p>
However, packages which are included in the <c>system</c> target, or are
dependencies of <c>system</c> target packages, should generally include a complete
dependency list (excluding bootstrap packages). This makes <c>emerge -e system</c>
possible when installing from a stage 1 or stage 2 tarball.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Basic Dependency Syntax</title>
<body>

<p>
A basic <c>DEPEND</c> specification might look like the following:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="dev-lang/ruby
    dev-ruby/ruby-gtk2
    dev-ruby/mysql-ruby"
</codesample>

<p>
Each atom is the full category and name of a package. Atoms are separated by
arbitrary whitespace <d/> convention is to specify one atom per line for
readability purposes. When specifying names, the category part should be treated
as mandatory.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Version Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes a particular version of a package is needed. Where this is known, it
should be specified. A simple example:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND=">=dev-libs/openssl-0.9.7d"
</codesample>

<p>
This states that at least version 0.9.7d of <c>openssl</c> is required.
</p>

<subsection>
<title>Version Specifiers</title>
<body>

<p>
Available version specifiers are:
</p>

<p>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Specifier</th>
    <th>Meaning</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>>=app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>Version 1.23 or later is required.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>>app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>A version strictly later than 1.23 is required.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>~app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>Version 1.23 (or any <c>1.23-r*</c>) is required.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>=app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>
      Exactly version 1.23 is required. If at all possible,
      use the <c>~</c> form to simplify revision bumps.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>&lt;=app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>Version 1.23 or older is required.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>&lt;app-misc/foo-1.23</c></ti>
    <ti>A version strictly before 1.23 is required.</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Ranged Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
To specify "version 2.x (not 1.x or 3.x)" of a package, it is necessary to use
the asterisk postfix. This is most commonly seen in situations like:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="gtk? ( =x11-libs/gtk+-1.2* )"
</codesample>

<p>
Note that the equals sign is mandatory, and that there is no dot before the
asterisk. Also note that when selecting all versions in a specific
<c>SLOT</c>, <c>SLOT</c> dependencies should be used (see below).
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Blockers</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes two packages cannot be installed in parallel. This is handled by
blockers. A blocker is specified as follows:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="!app-misc/foo"
</codesample>

<p>
Note that blockers are usually <e>runtime</e> rather than buildtime.
</p>

<p>
Specific versions can also be blocked:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="!&lt;app-misc/foo-1.3"
</codesample>

<p>
Blockers can be optional based upon <c>USE</c> flags as per normal
dependencies.
</p>

<p>
Blockers added to older ebuilds should not be expected to be retroactive.  If
the user already has the ebuild installed, any changes to the ebuild should not
be expected to make any difference.  This means that you should add the
blockers to whichever ebuild is the newest (even if it means that logically it
would seem backwards).  For example, certain versions of portage don't like
some versions of bash, but the blocker was put into bash because that was the
newer package that caused the issues.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SLOT Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to depend on a package in a specific <c>SLOT</c> you must specify
at least <c>EAPI="1"</c>.
</p>

<p>
To depend on a specific <c>SLOT</c>, <c>:SLOT</c> should be appended to
the package name, where 'SLOT' is the <c>SLOT</c> of the package wanted:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="qt3? ( x11-libs/qt:3 )
    gtk? ( x11-libs/gtk+:2 )
</codesample>

<subsection>
<title>Slot Operators</title>
<body>

<p>
In <c>EAPI="5"</c> and higher, you can use slot operators appended to the package
name to declare whether or not your package should be rebuilt after the versions
satisfying its runtime dependencies are updated to versions with a different slot
or <uri link="::general-concepts/slotting#Sub-Slots">sub-slot</uri>:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>:=</c> means that any slot is acceptable, and that your package should be
  rebuilt if the version best matching the runtime dependency is updated to a
  version with a different slot or subslot;</li>
  <li><c>:*</c> means that any slot is acceptable, and explicitly declares that
  changes in the slot or sub-slot can be ignored;</li>
  <li><c>:SLOT=</c> means that only the 'SLOT' slot is acceptable, and that your
  package should be rebuilt if the version matching the runtime dependency is
  updated to another version with this slot but with a different subslot;</li>
  <li><c>:SLOT</c> means that only the 'SLOT' slot is acceptable, and that changes
  in the sub-slot can be ignored (like in previous EAPIs).</li>
  <li><c>:SLOT/SUBSLOT</c> means a dependency on a specific slot and sub-slot pair,
  which can be useful for packages installing pre-built binaries that require a
  library with a particular soname version corresponding to the sub-slot.</li>
</ul>

<p>
For example:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="media-libs/cogl:1.0=
    gnutls? ( &gt;=net-libs/gnutls-2.8:= )"
</codesample>

</body>
</subsection>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>USE-Conditional Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
To depend upon a certain package if and only if a given <c>USE</c> flag is set:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="perl? ( dev-lang/perl )
    ruby? ( &gt;=dev-lang/ruby-1.8 )
    python? ( dev-lang/python )"
</codesample>

<p>
It is also possible to depend upon a certain package if a given <c>USE</c> flag is
<e>not</e> set:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="!crypt? ( net-misc/netkit-rsh )"
</codesample>

<p>
This should <b>not</b> be used for disabling a certain <c>USE</c> flag on a given
architecture. In order to do this, the architecture team should add the <c>USE</c>
flag to their <c>use.mask</c> file in the <c>profiles/arch</c>
directory of the Portage tree.
</p>

<p>
This can be nested:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="!build? (
    gcj? (
        gtk? (
            x11-libs/libXt
            x11-libs/libX11
            x11-libs/libXtst
            x11-proto/xproto
            x11-proto/xextproto
            >=x11-libs/gtk+-2.2
            x11-libs/pango
        )
        >=media-libs/libart_lgpl-2.1
    )
    >=sys-libs/ncurses-5.2-r2
    nls? ( sys-devel/gettext )
)"
</codesample>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>
Any of Many Dependencies
</title>
<body>

<p>
To depend on either <c>foo</c> or <c>bar</c>:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="|| ( app-misc/foo app-misc/bar )"
</codesample>

<p>
To depend on either <c>foo</c> or <c>bar</c> if the <c>baz</c> <c>USE</c> flag is set:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="baz? ( || ( app-misc/foo app-misc/bar ) )"
</codesample>

<subsection>
<title>Any of Many Versus USE</title>
<body>

<p>
Say <c>fnord</c> can be built against either <c>foo</c> or <c>bar</c>. Then a <c>USE</c>
flag is not necessary if and only if all of the following hold:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>fnord</c> is merged on a system which has <c>foo</c> and not <c>bar</c> installed.
    <c>foo</c> is then unmerged, and <c>bar</c> is installed. <c>fnord</c> must continue to
    work correctly.
  </li>
  <li>
    A binary package of <c>fnord</c> made on a system with <c>foo</c> and not <c>bar</c>
    can be taken and installed on a system with <c>bar</c> and not <c>foo</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Built with USE Dependencies</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to use built with use dependencies you must specify <c>EAPI="2"</c>.
</p>

<p>
Available specifiers are:
</p>

<p>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Specifier</th>
    <th>Meaning</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[bar]</c></ti>
    <ti>foo must have bar enabled.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[bar,baz]</c></ti>
    <ti>foo must have both bar and baz enabled.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[-bar,baz]</c></ti>
    <ti>foo must have bar disabled and baz enabled.</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>

<p>
There are also shortcuts for conditional situations:
</p>

<p>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Compact form</th>
    <th>Equivalent expanded form</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[bar?]</c></ti>
    <ti><c>bar? ( app-misc/foo[bar] ) !bar? ( app-misc/foo )</c></ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[!bar?]</c></ti>
    <ti><c>bar? ( app-misc/foo ) !bar? ( app-misc/foo[-bar] )</c></ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[bar=]</c></ti>
    <ti><c>bar? ( app-misc/foo[bar] ) !bar? ( app-misc/foo[-bar] )</c></ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><c>app-misc/foo[!bar=]</c></ti>
    <ti><c>bar? ( app-misc/foo[-bar] ) !bar? ( app-misc/foo[bar] )</c></ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Legacy Inverse USE-Conditional Dependency Syntax</title>
<body>

<p>
	Once upon a time the <c>:</c> conditional operator was allowed in <c>*DEPEND</c>:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="use-flag? ( app-misc/foo ) : ( app-misc/bar )"
</codesample>

<p>
<b>This syntax is no longer permitted</b>. It is exactly equivalent to the
following, which should be used instead:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
DEPEND="use-flag?  ( app-misc/foo )
    !use-flag? ( app-misc/bar )"
</codesample>

<p>
It is useful to recognise the legacy syntax and to know that it is no longer
valid.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
