<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/mirrors/">
<chapter>
<title>Mirrors</title>

<section>
<title>Automatic mirroring</title>

<body>
<p>
Packages will automatically have their <c>SRC_URI</c> components mirrored onto
Gentoo mirrors, including those hosted on the official Gentoo
Infrastructure (i.e. developer space at <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>). When
fetching, package manager checks
Gentoo mirrors first before trying the original upstream location.
</p>

<p>
This is generally desired behaviour <d/> upstream mirrors are prone to being
rearranged, tidied out or having files modified.
</p>
</body>

<subsection>
<title>Restricting automatic mirroring</title>
<body>
<p>
Three <c>RESTRICT</c> keywords can be used to control the mirroring process.
</p>

<p>
The <c>RESTRICT="mirror"</c> setting should be used if we cannot legally mirror
certain files; files will still be downloaded from the original locations.
</p>

<p>
The <c>RESTRICT="primaryuri"</c> setting causes Portage to try
original locations <e>first</e>, and then fall back to mirrors if necessary.
This should not be used in new ebuilds.
</p>

<p>
There is also <c>RESTRICT="fetch"</c>, which prevents Portage from trying to
fetch anything manually.
The <uri link="::ebuild-writing/functions/pkg_nofetch/">pkg_nofetch</uri>
function will be called if any <c>SRC_URI</c> components cannot be found.
This should only be used if a license requires it.
</p>
</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Replacing automatically mirrored files</title>
<body>
<p>
On rare occasions you may need to replace a file that is already mirrored.
This is usually the case when upstream remakes a release package. If this
is necessary, please use <c>SRC_URI</c> arrow to rename the file. For example:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
# upstream updated the distfile in place, so suffix it with _YYYYMMDD
SRC_URI="https://example.com/badupstream/${P}.tar.gz -&gt; ${P}_20191016.tar.gz"
</codesample>

<p>
Since Gentoo mirrors operate using local distfile names, they will automatically
fetch and start distributing the new version.
</p>

<p>
Updating an existing distfile is generally cause for concern and must be done
with care, see <uri link="::general-concepts/manifest/#Updating Manifests"/>.
</p>

<p>
More general information about the internals of mirroring can be found on <uri
link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Infrastructure/Mirrors/Distfile_Mirroring_System">
Infrastructure project's Distfile Mirroring System page</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</subsection>


<subsection>
<title>Suitable download hosts</title>
<body>
<p>
If you have to host a source file (patch or tarball) yourself, as long as it
can be freely distributed (by license and legality), you're suggested to use
your developer's space at <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>. Since external overlays may
depend on your patches/tarballs, using the dev space at <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>
keeps the distfiles at a stable and reliable infrastructure. If you retire,
other developers can take over your distfiles and place them into their own
devspace.
</p>

<p>
Previous policy was to use <c>mirror://gentoo</c> directly, but this is now
prohibited, as that wouldn't allow to have long-term availability and
traceability of the source files, which might be a requirement of the license.
</p>

<p>
When you upload the distfile to <c>dev.gentoo.org:~/public_html</c>, ensure that
your file and its parent directories have the correct permissions, so they're
accessible. An example <c>SRC_URI</c> referencing a distfile mirrored this way
is as follows:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
SRC_URI="https://dev.gentoo.org/~myname/distfiles/${P}.tar.gz"
</codesample>

<p>
where <c>myname</c> refers to the username of the developer.
</p>

<p>
If the upstream download location for a package uses a non-standard TCP port
(anything other than 21, 80 or 443), you <e>must</e> manually mirror the files.
Not doing so can cause all kinds of problems with strict firewalls.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mirroring process</title>

<body>
<figure short="Mirroring Process" link="diagram.png"
  caption="Diagram showing the mirroring process." />
</body>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Third-party mirrors</title>
  <body>
    <p>
      Usage of third-party mirrors and the <c>mirror://</c>
      pseudo-protocol is described in the
      <uri link="::ebuild-writing/variables/#Third-party mirrors"><c>SRC_URI</c>
      variable documentation</uri>.
    </p>
  </body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
