<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="ebuild-writing/eapi/">
<chapter>
<title>EAPI Usage and Description</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:PMS">Package Manager
Specification (PMS)</uri> is a standardization effort to ensure that the
ebuild file format, the ebuild repository format (of which the Gentoo
repository is Gentoo's main incarnation) as well as behaviour of the package
managers interacting with these ebuilds is properly written down and agreed
upon.
</p>

<p>
EAPI is a version defined in ebuilds and other package manager related files
which informs the package manager about the file syntax and content. It is,
in effect, the version of the package manager specification (PMS) that the
file adheres to.
</p>

<p>
This section provides usage and descriptions of the different EAPIs.
</p>

</body>

<section>
<title>Usage of EAPIs</title>
<body>

<important>
An overview about the important features of each EAPI is provided in the
appendix of the Package Manager Specification.  The two-page leaflet
can be printed out, consulted for reference and is available
as <c>app-doc/pms</c> in the main tree.
</important>

<p>
You must set the EAPI variable by specifying it at the top of the ebuild:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
# Copyright 1999-2021 Gentoo Authors
# Distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License v2

EAPI=7
</codesample>

<note>
Most developers prefer to set the EAPI version without quotes. However, the PMS
allows single and double quotes as well.
</note>

<important>
EAPI must only be defined in ebuild files, not eclasses. (eclasses may have
EAPI-conditional code)
</important>

<p>
When writing new ebuilds developers can choose whatever EAPI they think
is the best.  Using the features of the latest EAPI is encouraged.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>EAPIs 0 to 4</title>
<body>

<p>
EAPIs 0 to 4 are obsolete and must no longer be used. Refer to the Package
Manager Specification for details about them.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>EAPI 5</title>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 5 Metadata</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>REQUIRED_USE supports new at-most-one-of operator</dt>
  <dd>
    The new <b>at-most-one-of</b> operator consists of the string <c>??</c>,
    and is satisfied if zero or one (but no more) of its child elements is
    matched.
  </dd>
  <dt>SLOT supports optional "sub-slot" part</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>SLOT</c> variable may contain an optional <b>sub-slot</b> part that
    follows the regular slot and is delimited by a <c>/</c> character.
    The sub-slot must be a valid slot name. The sub-slot is used to represent
    cases in which an upgrade to a new version of a package with a different
    sub-slot may require dependent packages to be rebuilt. When the sub-slot
    part is omitted from the SLOT definition, the package is considered to have
    an implicit sub-slot which is equal to the regular slot.
  </dd>
  <dt>Slot operators and sub-slots in dependencies</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    A slot dependency may contain an optional sub-slot part that follows the
    regular slot and is delimited by a <c>/</c> character. This can be useful
    for packages installing pre-built binaries that require a library with a
    specific soname version which corresponds to the sub-slot. For example:
    </p>
<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="dev-libs/foo:0/3"
</codesample>
    <p>
    Package dependency specifications can use <b>slot operators</b> to clarify
    what should happen if the slot and/or sub-slot of a runtime dependency
    changes:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <c>:*</c> Indicates that any slot value is acceptable. In addition,
        for runtime dependencies, indicates that the package specifying the
        dependency will not break if the package matching the dependency is
        replaced by a different matching package with a different slot and/or
        sub-slot.
      </li>
      <li>
        <c>:=</c> Indicates that any slot value is acceptable. In addition,
        for runtime dependencies, indicates that the package specifying the
        dependency will break unless there is available a package matching
        the dependency and whose slot and sub-slot are equal to the slot and
        sub-slot of the best installed version that had matched this dependency
        at the time when the package specifying this dependency had been
        installed.
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        <c>:slot=</c> Indicates that only a specific slot value is acceptable,
        and otherwise behaves identically to the <c>:=</c> operator.
        </p>
        <note>
        use <c>:slot/subslot</c> without a <c>=</c> to depend on a specific
        slot and sub-slot pair; it's a syntax error to use <c>:slot/subslot=</c>
        in an ebuild.
        </note>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    The <c>:slot</c> dependency syntax continues to behave like in EAPI=4 or
    earlier, i.e. it indicates that only the specific slot value is acceptable,
    but the package will not break when the version matching the runtime
    dependency is replaced by a version with a different sub-slot.
    </p>
    <p>
    For example:
    </p>
<codesample lang="ebuild">
RDEPEND="dev-libs/foo:2=
    &gt;=dev-libs/bar-0.9:=
    media-gfx/baz:*
    x11-misc/wombat:0"
</codesample>
    <p>
    means that the package should be rebuilt when <c>foo:2</c> or
    <c>&gt;=bar-0.9</c> are upgraded to versions with different subslots,
    but that changes in subslots of <c>baz</c> or <c>wombat:0</c> should be
    ignored.
    </p>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 5 Profiles</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Profile stable USE forcing and masking</dt>
  <dd>
    In profile directories with an EAPI supporting stable masking, new USE
    configuration files are supported: <c>use.stable.mask</c>,
    <c>use.stable.force</c>, <c>package.use.stable.mask</c> and
    <c>package.use.stable.force</c>. These files behave similarly to previously
    supported USE configuration files, except that they only influence packages
    that are merged due to a stable keyword.
  </dd>
</dl>
</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 5 Helpers</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>econf adds --disable-silent-rules</dt>
  <dd>
    This option will automatically be passed if <c>--disable-silent-rules</c>
    occurs in the output of <c>configure --help</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt>new* commands can read from standard input</dt>
  <dd>
    Standard input is read when the first parameter is <c>-</c> (a hyphen).
  </dd>
  <dt>New option --host-root for {has,best}_version</dt>
  <dd>
    This option <c>--host-root</c> will cause the query to apply to the host
    root instead of ROOT.
  </dd>
  <dt>New doheader helper function</dt>
  <dd>
    Installs the given header files into <c>/usr/include/</c>. If option
    <c>-r</c> is specified, descends recursively into any directories given.
  </dd>
  <dt>New usex helper function</dt>
  <dd>
    <!-- We probably need an example here -->
<pre>
USAGE: usex &lt;USE flag&gt; [true output] [false output] [true suffix] [false suffix]
DESCRIPTION:
If USE flag is set, echo [true output][true suffix] (defaults to "yes"),
 otherwise echo [false output][false suffix] (defaults to "no").
</pre>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 5 Phases</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>src_test supports parallel tests</dt>
  <dd>
    Unlike older EAPIs, the default <c>src_test</c> implementation will not
    pass the -j1 option to emake.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 5 Variables</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>EBUILD_PHASE_FUNC</dt>
  <dd>
    During execution of an ebuild phase function (such as <c>pkg_setup</c> or
    <c>src_unpack</c>), the <c>EBUILD_PHASE_FUNC</c> variable will contain the
    name of the phase function that is currently executing.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>EAPI 6</title>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 6 Bash version</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Bash version</dt>
  <dd>
    Ebuilds can use features of Bash version 4.2 (was 3.2 before).
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 6 Ebuild Environment</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Locale settings</dt>
  <dd>
    Behaviour of case modification and collation order (<c>LC_CTYPE</c> and
    <c>LC_COLLATE</c>) are guaranteed to be the same as in the C locale, as far
    as characters in the ASCII range are concerned.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>failglob</c> enabled</dt>
  <dd>
    For <c>EAPI=6</c>, the <c>failglob</c> option of bash is set in the global
    scope of ebuilds. If set, failed pattern matches during filename expansion
    result in an error when the ebuild is being sourced.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 6 Phases</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Update default implementation of <c>src_prepare</c></dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    This phase is no longer a no-op, it supports applying patches via the
    <c>PATCHES</c> variable and applying user patches via <c>eapply_user</c>.
    The default <c>src_prepare</c> looks like this:
    </p>
<codesample lang="ebuild">
src_prepare() {
    if [[ $(declare -p PATCHES 2&gt;/dev/null) == "declare -a"* ]]; then
        [[ -n ${PATCHES[@]} ]] &amp;&amp; eapply "${PATCHES[@]}"
    else
        [[ -n ${PATCHES} ]] &amp;&amp; eapply ${PATCHES}
    fi
    eapply_user
}
</codesample>
  </dd>
  <dt>New <c>src_install</c> Phase Function</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    This phase uses the new <c>einstalldocs</c> function for installation of
    documentation. The default <c>src_install</c> looks like this:
    </p>
<codesample lang="ebuild">
src_install() {
    if [[ -f Makefile ]] || [[ -f GNUmakefile ]] || [[ -f makefile ]]; then
        emake DESTDIR="${D}" install
    fi
    einstalldocs
}
</codesample>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 6 Helpers</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt><c>einstall</c> banned</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>einstall</c> helper has been banned with <c>EAPI=6</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>dohtml</c> deprecated</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>dohtml</c> helper has been deprecated with <c>EAPI=6</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>nonfatal die</c></dt>
  <dd>
    When <c>die</c> or <c>assert</c> are called under the <c>nonfatal</c>
    command and with the <c>-n</c> option, they will not abort the build
    process but return with an error.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>eapply</c> support</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>eapply</c> command is a simplified substitute for <c>epatch</c>
    (from <c>eutils.eclass</c>), implemented in the package manager.
    The patches from its file or directory arguments are applied using patch
    <c>-p1</c>, but it accepts <c>patch(1)</c> options from GNU patch to
    override default behavior.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>eapply_user</c> support</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The <c>eapply_user</c> command permits the package manager to apply
    user-provided patches. It must be called from every <c>src_prepare</c>
    function.
    </p>
    <note>
    <c>eapply_user</c> doesn't need to be called explicitly when default
    <c>src_prepare</c> is called.
    </note>
  </dd>
  <dt><c>econf</c> adds <c>--docdir</c> and <c>--htmldir</c></dt>
  <dd>
    Options <c>--docdir</c> and <c>--htmldir</c> are passed to
    <c>configure</c>, in addition to the existing options.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>in_iuse</c> support</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>in_iuse</c> function returns <c>true</c> if the given parameter is
    available in the ebuilds <c>USE</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>unpack</c> changes</dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <c>unpack</c> supports relative paths without leading <c>./</c>
        (<c>unpack foo/bar.tar.gz</c> is valid as relative path).
      </li>
      <li><c>unpack</c> supports <c>.txz</c> (xz compressed tarball).</li>
      <li><c>unpack</c> matches filename extensions case-insensitively.</li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
  <dt><c>einstalldocs</c> support</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>einstalldocs</c> function will install the files specified by the
    <c>DOCS</c> variable (or a default set of files if <c>DOCS</c> is unset)
    and by the <c>HTML_DOCS</c> variable.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>get_libdir</c> support</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>get_libdir</c> command outputs the <c>lib*</c> directory basename
    suitable for the current ABI.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>EAPI 7</title>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 7 Terminology</title>
<body>

<p>
Documents may use the following terms to better describe dependency and
installation targets.
</p>

<dl>
  <dt><c>CHOST</c></dt>
  <dd>
    The system that will be running the installed package.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>CBUILD</c></dt>
  <dd>
    The system used to build packages. When not cross-compiling,
    CBUILD == CHOST.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>CTARGET</c></dt>
  <dd>
    Used in certain cross-compilations, often empty value.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 7 Variables</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt><c>PORTDIR</c> and <c>ECLASSDIR</c> are removed</dt>
  <dd>
    <c>PORTDIR</c> and <c>ECLASSDIR</c> are no longer defined and cannot be
    used in ebuilds to access these directories.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>DESTTREE</c> and <c>INSDESTTREE</c> are removed</dt>
  <dd>
    The unintended exported variables <c>PORTDIR</c> and <c>ECLASSDIR</c>
    cannot be used in ebuilds to manipulate installation paths. Use <c>into</c>
    or <c>insinto</c>, respectively, instead.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>D</c>, <c>ED</c>, <c>ROOT</c>, and <c>EROOT</c> modified</dt>
  <dd>
    These variables no longer contain a trailing slash with <c>EAPI=7</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>BDEPEND</c> added</dt>
  <dd>
    Previously, all build-time tools and libraries went into the <c>DEPEND</c>.
    Now, built-time dependencies are split into <c>DEPEND</c> and
    <c>BDEPEND</c>. The difference is simply that <c>BDEPEND</c> are
    dependencies to be executed on the CBUILD. <c>DEPEND</c> remains for other
    dependencies, such as libraries, for the CHOST. This improves the
    cross-compilation support.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>BROOT</c> added</dt>
  <dd>
    <c>BROOT</c> is the absolute path to the root directory, including any
    prefix, containing build dependencies satisfied by BDEPEND, typically
    executable build tools.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>SYSROOT</c> and <c>ESYSROOT</c> added</dt>
  <dd>
    <c>SYSROOT</c> is the location of where dependencies in <c>DEPEND</c> are
    installed. <c>ESYSROOT</c> is <c>SYSROOT</c> with <c>EPREFIX</c> appended.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>ENV_UNSET</c> added</dt>
  <dd>
    A whitespace delimited list of variables to be removed from the build
    environment.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 7 Metadata</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Empty groupings are banned</dt>
  <dd>
    Groupings which are empty, such as <c>DEPEND="|| ( ${empty_var} )"</c>
    will now generate an error. Furthermore, conditions within groupings are
    more strictly enforced. For example, <c>REQUIRED_USE="|| ( foo? ( bar )
    baz? ( zoinks )"</c> would previously work with <c>USE="-foo -baz"</c>
    now requires either <c>USE="foo bar"</c> or <c>USE="baz zoinks"</c>.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 7 Profiles</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt><c>package.provided</c> banned</dt>
  <dd>
    Profiles may no longer contain a <c>package.provided</c> file with
    <c>EAPI=7</c>.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 7 Helpers</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt><c>dohtml</c> banned</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>dohtml</c> helper has been banned with <c>EAPI=7</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>dolib</c> and <c>libopts</c> banned</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>dolib</c> helper and the associated <c>libopts</c> have been banned
    with <c>EAPI=7</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>has_version</c> and <c>best_version</c> changes</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    <c>has_version</c> and <c>best_version</c> now support an optional switch
    to determine which type of dependencies to check.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><c>-r</c> (the default) will check runtime dependencies (RDEPEND)</li>
      <li><c>-d</c> will check CHOST build-time dependencies (DEPEND)</li>
      <li><c>-b</c> will check CBUILD build-time dependencies (BDEPEND)</li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
  <dt>Version manipulation and comparison commands</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    EAPI=7 introduced three commands for common version number operations.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><c>ver_cut</c> obtains substrings of a version string</li>
      <li><c>ver_rs</c> replaces separators in a version string</li>
      <li><c>ver_test</c> compares two versions</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    See <uri link="::ebuild-writing/variables/#Version and Name Formatting Issues"/>
    for examples of common uses or
    <uri link="https://dev.gentoo.org/~mgorny/articles/the-ultimate-guide-to-eapi-7.html#version-manipulation-and-comparison-commands">
    an in-depth look</uri>
    </p>
  </dd>
  <dt>New function <c>eqawarn</c></dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>eqawarn</c> helper has been added with <c>EAPI=7</c>. This function
    is to alert developers to a deprecated feature. Previously, this was
    contained in <c>eutils</c> eclass which is no longer necessary.
  </dd>
  <dt>New function <c>dostrip</c></dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>dostrip</c> helper has been added with <c>EAPI=7</c>. This function
    controls whether or not to strip a binary. <c>dostrip -x [file]</c> will
    exclude a binary from being stripped. Conversely, when combined with
    RESTRICT=strip, <c>dostrip [file]</c> selects a binary file to be stripped.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>die</c> and <c>assert</c> changes</dt>
  <dd>
    These commands are now safe to use in a subshell and act as if they were
    called in the main process.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>nonfatal</c> changes</dt>
  <dd>
    The <c>nonfatal</c> command now works for shell functions and subprocesses.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>domo</c> behaviour changed</dt>
  <dd>
    <c>domo</c> (for localizations) now ignores the <c>into</c> directives.
    This follows similar commands like <c>doinfo</c> and <c>doman</c>.
  </dd>
  <dt><c>econf</c> changes</dt>
  <dd>
    The cross-compilation options <c>--build</c> and <c>--target</c> options
    to specify <c>CBUILD</c> and <c>CTARGET</c> respectively have been added
    and are retro-active to all EAPIs. In addition, if the build supports
    <c>--with-sysroot</c>, the correct value will be passed such that normal
    and cross-compilations succeed.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>EAPI 8</title>
<body>

<note>
This section is based on
<uri link="https://mgorny.pl/articles/the-ultimate-guide-to-eapi-8.html">
The ultimate guide to EAPI 8</uri> by Michał Górny.
</note>

</body>

<subsection>
<title>EAPI 8 tree layout</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Less strict naming rules for updates directory</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Up to EAPI 7, the files in the <c>profiles/updates</c> directory had to
    follow strict naming by quarters like <c>2Q-2021</c>, indicating the
    quarter and the year when they were added. Such a choice of name had the
    side effect that lexical sorting of filenames was unsuitable.
    </p>

    <p>
    In EAPI 8, the naming requirement is removed. Eventually, this will allow
    switching to a more convenient scheme sorted by year. Different lengths
    of time periods will also be possible.
    </p>

    <p>
    Note that this change actually requires changing the repository EAPI
    (found in <c>profiles/eapi</c>), so it will not affect Gentoo for at least
    the next two years.
    </p>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>EAPI 8 ebuild format</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Bash version is now 5.0</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The Bash version used for ebuilds is changed from 4.2 to 5.0. This means
    not only that ebuilds are now permitted to use features provided by the new
    Bash version but also the <c>BASH_COMPAT</c> value used for the ebuild
    environment is updated, switching the shell behaviour.
    </p>

    <p>
    The only really relevant difference in behaviour is:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
        Quotes are now removed from the RHS argument of a
        <c>"${var/.../"..."}"</c> substitution:
        </p>

<pre>
var=foo
echo "${var/foo/"bar"}"
</pre>

        <p>
        The above snippet yields <c>"bar"</c> in Bash 4.2 but just <c>bar</c>
        in 4.3+.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    Potentially interesting new features include:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
        Negative subscripts can now be used to set and unset array elements
        (Bash 4.3+):
        </p>

<pre>
$ foo=( 1 2 3 )
$ foo[-1]=4
$ unset 'foo[-2]'
$ declare -p foo
declare -a foo=([0]="1" [2]="4")
</pre>

      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        Nameref variables are introduced that work as references to other
        variables (4.3+):
        </p>

<pre>
$ foo=( 1 2 3 )
$ declare -n bar=foo
$ echo "${bar[@]}"
1 2 3
$ bar[0]=4
$ echo "${foo[@]}"
4 2 3
$ declare -n baz=foo[1]
$ echo "${baz}"
2
$ baz=100
$ echo "${bar[@]}"
4 100 3
</pre>

      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        The <c>[[ -v ... ]]</c> test operator can be used with array indices
        to test for array elements being set (4.3+). The two following lines
        are now equivalent:
        </p>

<pre>
[[ -n ${foo[3]+1} ]]
[[ -v foo[3] ]]
</pre>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        <c>mapfile</c> (AKA <c>readarray</c>) now accepts a delimiter via
        <c>-d</c>, with a <c>-t</c> option to strip it from read data
        (Bash 4.4+). The two following solutions to grab output from
        <c>find(1)</c> are now equivalent:
        </p>

<pre>
# old solution
local x files=()
while read -d '' -r x; do
	files+=( "${x}" )
done &lt; &lt;(find -print0)

# new solution
local files=()
mapfile -d '' -t files &lt; &lt;(find -print0)
</pre>

      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        A new set of transformations is available via <c>${foo@...}</c>
        parameter expansion (4.4+), e.g. to print a value with necessary
        quoting:
        </p>

<pre>
$ var="foo 'bar' baz"
$ echo "${var@Q}"
'foo '\''bar'\'' baz'
</pre>

        <p>
        For more details, see: <c>info bash</c> or the
        <uri link="https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/html_node/Shell-Parameter-Expansion.html">
        Bash reference manual</uri>.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        <c>local -</c> can be used to limit single-letter (mangled via
        <c>set</c>) shell option changes to the scope of the function, and
        restore them upon returning from it (4.4+). The following two functions
        are now equivalent:
        </p>

<pre>
# old solution
func() {
	local prev_shopt=$(shopt -p -o noglob)
	set -o noglob
	${prev_shopt}
}

# new solution
func() {
	local -
	set -o noglob
}
</pre>

        <p>
        The complete information on all changes and new features can be found
        in the
        <uri link="https://git.savannah.gnu.org/cgit/bash.git/tree/NEWS?h=bash-5.0">
        Bash 5.0 (and earlier) release notes</uri>.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>EAPI 8 variables</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>Selective fetch/mirror restriction</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Before EAPI 8, fetch and mirror restrictions applied globally. That is,
    if you needed to apply the respective restriction to at least one distfile,
    you had to apply it to them all. However, sometimes packages used a
    combination of proprietary and free distfiles, the latter including e.g.
    third party patches, artwork. Until now, they had to be mirror-restricted
    completely.
    </p>

    <p>
    EAPI 8 allows undoing fetch and mirror restriction for individual files.
    To use this, set <c>RESTRICT</c> as before, then use the special
    <c>fetch+</c> prefix to specify URLs that can be fetched from, or the
    <c>mirror+</c> prefix to reenable mirroring of individual files.
    </p>

    <p>
    Similarly to how the <c>fetch</c> restriction implies a <c>mirror</c>
    restriction, the <c>mirror</c> override implies a <c>fetch</c> override.
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
EAPI=8

SRC_URI="
	${P}.tgz
	fetch+https://example.com/${P}-patch-1.tgz
	mirror+https://example.com/${P}-fanstuff.tgz"

RESTRICT="fetch"
</codesample>

    <p>
    The following table summarises the new behaviour:
    </p>

    <table>
      <tr>
        <th><c>RESTRICT</c></th>
        <th>URI prefix</th>
        <th>Fetching</th>
        <th>Mirroring</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>(none)</ti>
        <ti>(any)</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti rowspan="2">mirror</ti>
        <ti>(none) / fetch+</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
        <ti>prohibited</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>mirror+</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti rowspan="3">fetch</ti>
        <ti>(none)</ti>
        <ti>prohibited</ti>
        <ti>prohibited</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>fetch+</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
        <ti>prohibited</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>mirror+</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
        <ti>allowed</ti>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </dd>

  <dt>Install-time dependencies (<c>IDEPEND</c>)</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The primary use for install-time dependencies is to specify dependencies
    that are needed during the <c>pkg_postinst</c> phase and that can be
    unmerged afterwards. That's pretty much the same as <c>RDEPEND</c>, except
    for the unmerging part <d/> and uninstalling a few tools did not seem a
    goal justifying another dependency type.
    </p>

    <p>
    With cross-compilation support in EAPI 7, a new dependency type focused
    on the build host (<c>CBUILD</c>) tools was added <d/> <c>BDEPEND</c>.
    Unfortunately, this had missed the important use case of running
    executables installed to the target system when cross-compiling.
    <c>RDEPEND</c> was no longer a suitable method of pulling in tools for
    <c>pkg_postinst</c>; and since <c>BDEPEND</c> is not used when installing
    from a binary package, something new was needed.
    </p>

    <p>
    This is where <c>IDEPEND</c> comes in. It is roughly to <c>RDEPEND</c> what
    <c>BDEPEND</c> is to <c>DEPEND</c>. Similarly to <c>BDEPEND</c>,
    it specifies packages that must be built for the <c>CBUILD</c> triplet
    and installed into <c>BROOT</c> (and therefore queried using
    <c>has_version -b</c>). However, similarly to <c>RDEPEND</c>, it is used
    when the package is being merged rather than built from source.
    It is guaranteed to be satisfied throughout <c>pkg_preinst</c> and
    <c>pkg_postinst</c>, and it can be uninstalled afterwards.
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
EAPI=8

inherit xdg-utils

IDEPEND="dev-util/desktop-file-utils"

pkg_postinst() {
	xdg_desktop_database_update
}

pkg_postrm() {
	xdg_desktop_database_update
}
</codesample>

    <p>
    In the example provided above, the ebuild needs to be update the icon cache
    upon being installed or uninstalled. By placing the respective tool in
    <c>IDEPEND</c>, the ebuild requests it to be available at the time of
    <c>pkg_postinst</c>. When cross-compiling, the tool will be built for
    <c>CBUILD</c> and therefore directly executable by the ebuild.
    </p>

    <p>
    The dependency types table for EAPI 8 is presented below.
    </p>

    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Dependency type</th>
        <th>BDEPEND</th>
        <th>IDEPEND</th>
        <th>DEPEND</th>
        <th>RDEPEND</th>
        <th>PDEPEND</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Present at</th>
        <ti>build</ti>
        <ti>install</ti>
        <ti>build</ti>
        <ti>install</ti>
        <ti>n/a</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Binary compatible with</th>
        <ti colspan="2">CBUILD</ti>
        <ti colspan="3">CHOST</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Base unprefixed path</th>
        <ti colspan="2"><c>/</c></ti>
        <ti>SYSROOT</ti>
        <ti colspan="2">ROOT</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Relevant offset-prefix</th>
        <ti colspan="2">BROOT</ti>
        <ti>EPREFIX (unless SYSROOT != ROOT)</ti>
        <ti colspan="2">EPREFIX</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Path combined with prefix</th>
        <ti colspan="2">BROOT</ti>
        <ti>ESYSROOT</ti>
        <ti colspan="2">EROOT</ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>PM query command option</th>
        <ti colspan="2"><c>-b</c></ti>
        <ti><c>-d</c></ti>
        <ti colspan="2"><c>-r</c></ti>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </dd>

  <dt>
    <c>PROPERTIES</c> and <c>RESTRICT</c> are now accumulated across eclasses
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Up to EAPI 7, <c>PROPERTIES</c> and <c>RESTRICT</c> were treated like
    regular Bash variables when sourcing eclasses. This meant that if an eclass
    or an ebuild wanted to modify them, they had to explicitly append to them,
    e.g. via <c>+=</c>. This was inconsistent with how some other variables
    (but not all) were handled, and confusing to developers. For example,
    consider the following snippet:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
EAPI=7

inherit git-r3

PROPERTIES+=" interactive"
</codesample>

    <p>
    Note how you needed to append to <c>PROPERTIES</c> set by git-r3 eclass,
    otherwise the ebuild would have overwritten it. In EAPI 8, you can finally
    do the following instead:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
EAPI=8

inherit git-r3

PROPERTIES="interactive"
</codesample>

    <p>
    Now the complete list of metadata variables accumulated across eclasses
    and ebuilds includes: <c>IUSE</c>, <c>REQUIRED_USE</c>, <c>*DEPEND</c>,
    <c>PROPERTIES</c>, <c>RESTRICT</c>. Variables that are not treated this way
    are: <c>EAPI</c>, <c>HOMEPAGE</c>, <c>SRC_URI</c>, <c>LICENSE</c>,
    <c>KEYWORDS</c>. <c>EAPI</c> and <c>KEYWORDS</c> are not supposed to be set
    in eclasses; as for the others, there appears to be a valid use case for
    eclasses providing default values and the ebuilds being able to override
    them.
    </p>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>EAPI 8 phase functions</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt><c>pkg_*</c> phases now run in a dedicated empty directory</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Before EAPI 8, the initial working directory was specified for <c>src_*</c>
    phases only. For other phases (i.e. <c>pkg_*</c> phases), ebuilds were not
    supposed to assume any particular directory. In EAPI 8, these phases are
    guaranteed to be started in a dedicated empty directory.
    </p>

    <p>
    The idea of using an empty directory is pretty simple <d/> if there are no
    files in it, the risk of unexpected and hard to predict interactions of
    tools with their current working directory is minimized.
    </p>
  </dd>

  <dt>
    <c>PATCHES</c> no longer permits options
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The <c>eapply</c> invocation in the default <c>src_prepare</c>
    implementation has been changed to:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
eapply -- "${PATCHES[@]}"
</codesample>

    <p>
    This ensures that all items in the <c>PATCHES</c> variable are treated
    as path names. As a side effect, it is no longer possible to specify
    <c>patch</c> options via the <c>PATCHES</c> variable. Such hacks were never
    used in the Gentoo repository but they have been spotted in
    user-contributed ebuilds. The following will no longer work:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
PATCHES=( -p0 "${FILESDIR}"/${P}-foo.patch )
</codesample>

    <p>
    Instead, you will need to invoke <c>eapply</c> explicitly, see the example
    below. Alternatively, rebase the patch level.
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
src_prepare() {
	eapply -p0 "${FILESDIR}"/${P}-foo.patch
	eapply_user
}
</codesample>

  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>EAPI 8 commands</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>New econf-passed options</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The <c>econf</c> helper has been modified to pass two more options to
    the configure script if the <c>--help</c> text indicates that they are
    supported. These are:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li><c>--datarootdir="${EPREFIX}"/usr/share</c></li>
      <li><c>--disable-static</c></li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    The former option defines the base directory that is used to determine
    locations for system/desktop-specific data files, e.g. .desktop files and
    various kinds of documentation. This is necessary for ebuilds that override
    <c>--prefix</c>, as the default path is relative to it.
    </p>

    <p>
    The latter option disables building static libraries by default. This is
    part of the ongoing effort to disable unconditional install of static
    libraries
    (<uri link="https://projects.gentoo.org/qa/policy-guide/installed-files.html#pg0302">
    Gentoo Policy Guide, Installation of static libraries</uri>).
    </p>
  </dd>

  <dt><c>dosym -r</c> to create relative symlinks</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Relative symlink targets tend to be more reliable. Consider the two
    following examples:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
dosym "${EPREFIX}"/usr/lib/frobnicate/frobnicate /usr/bin/frobnicate
dosym ../lib/frobnicate/frobnicate /usr/bin/frobnicate
</codesample>

    <p>
    The first line creates a symlink using an absolute path. The problem with
    that is if you mount your Gentoo system in a subdirectory of your root
    filesystem (e.g. for recovery), the symlink will point at the wrong
    location. Using relative symlinks (as demonstrated on the second line)
    guarantees that the symlink will work independently of where the filesystem
    is mounted.
    </p>

    <p>
    There is also fact that you need to explicitly prepend <c>${EPREFIX}</c>
    to the absolute paths passed as the first argument of <c>dosym</c>. Using
    a relative target avoids the problem altogether and makes it less likely to
    forget about the prefix.
    </p>

    <p>
    However, in some instances, determining the relative path could be hard or
    inconvenient. This is especially the case if one (or both) of the paths
    comes from an external tool. To make it easier, EAPI 8 adds a new <c>-r</c>
    option that makes <c>dosym</c> create a relative symlink to the specified
    path (similarly to <c>ln -r</c>):
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
dosym -r /usr/lib/frobnicate/frobnicate /usr/bin/frobnicate
</codesample>

    <p>
    Note that in this case, you do not pass <c>${EPREFIX}</c>. The helper
    determines the <e>logical</e> relative path to the first argument and
    creates the appropriate relative symlink. It is very important here to
    understand that this function does not handle physical paths, i.e. it will
    work only if there are no directory symlinks along the way that would
    result in <c>..</c> resolving to a different path. For example, the
    following will not work:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
dosym bar/foo /usr/lib/foo
dosym -r /usr/lib/zomg /usr/lib/foo/zomg
</codesample>

    <p>
    The logical path from <c>/usr/lib/foo/zomg</c> to <c>/usr/lib/zomg</c> is
    <c>../zomg</c>. However, since <c>/usr/lib/foo</c> is actually a symlink to
    <c>/usr/lib/bar/foo</c>, <c>/usr/lib/foo/..</c> resolves to
    <c>/usr/lib/bar</c>. If you need to account for such directory symlinks,
    you need to specify the correct path explicitly:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
dosym bar/foo /usr/lib/foo
dosym ../../zomg /usr/lib/foo/zomg
</codesample>

  </dd>

  <dt>
    <c>insopts</c> and <c>exeopts</c> now apply to <c>doins</c>
    and <c>doexe</c> only
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    In previous EAPIs, there was an inconsistency in how <c>insopts</c> and
    <c>exeopts</c> applied to various helpers. In particular, the majority of
    helpers (e.g. <c>dobin</c>, <c>dodoc</c> and so on) ignored the options
    specified via these helpers but a few did not.
    </p>

    <p>
    EAPI 8 changes the behaviour of the following helpers that used to respect
    <c>insopts</c> or <c>exeopts</c>:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li><c>doconfd</c></li>
      <li><c>doenvd</c></li>
      <li><c>doheader</c></li>
      <li><c>doinitd</c></li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    In EAPI 8, they always use the default options. As a result, <c>insopts</c>
    now only affects <c>doins</c>/<c>newins</c>, and <c>exeopts</c> only
    affects <c>doexe</c>/<c>newexe</c>. Furthermore, <c>diropts</c> does not
    affect the directories implicitly created by these helpers.
    </p>
  </dd>

  <dt><c>usev</c> now accepts a second argument</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    The <c>usev</c> helper was introduced to provide the historical Portage
    behaviour of outputting the USE flag name on match. In EAPI 8, it has been
    extended, in order to provide an alternative to three-argument <c>usex</c>
    with an empty third argument (the two-argument <c>usex</c> variant uses a
    default of <c>no</c> for the false branch).
    </p>

    <p>
    In other words, the following two calls are now equivalent:
    </p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
$(usex foo --enable-foo '')
$(usev foo --enable-foo)
</codesample>

    <p>
    This is particularly useful with custom build systems that accept
    individual <c>--enable</c> or <c>--disable</c> options but not their
    counterparts.
    </p>

    <p>
    As a result, <c>usev</c> and <c>usex</c> can now be used to achieve all the
    common (and less common) output needs as summarized in the following table.
    </p>

    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Variant</th>
        <th>True</th>
        <th>False</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>usev <e>flag</e></ti>
        <ti><e>flag</e></ti>
        <ti></ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>usev <e>flag</e> <e>true</e></ti>
        <ti><e>true</e></ti>
        <ti></ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>usex <e>flag</e></ti>
        <ti><c>yes</c></ti>
        <ti><c>no</c></ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>usex <e>flag</e> <e>true</e></ti>
        <ti><e>true</e></ti>
        <ti><c>no</c></ti>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <ti>usex <e>flag</e> <e>true</e> <e>false</e></ti>
        <ti><e>true</e></ti>
        <ti><e>false</e></ti>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </dd>

  <dt><c>hasq</c>, <c>hasv</c> and <c>useq</c> functions have been banned</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    In its early days, the <c>use</c> helper would print the USE flag name
    if it matched, in addition to its boolean exit status. Later, a quiet
    <c>useq</c> and a verbose <c>usev</c> helper were added, and <c>use</c> was
    made quiet by default. The same changes were applied to <c>has</c>.
    </p>

    <p>
    Fast forward to EAPI 7, there are still three variants of <c>use</c>
    and three variants of <c>has</c>. The base variant that is quiet, the
    <c>useq</c>/<c>hasq</c> variant that is equivalent to the base variant,
    and the verbose <c>usev</c>/<c>hasv</c> variant.
    </p>

    <p>
    Obviously, adding a second argument to <c>hasv</c> was not possible, so its
    behaviour would have become inconsistent with <c>usev</c> in EAPI 8. Since 
    <c>hasv</c> was not used in the Gentoo repository, it has been removed,
    along with <c>hasq</c> and <c>useq</c> which were considered deprecated
    since 2011.
    </p>
  </dd>

  <dt>unpack removes support for 7-Zip, LHA and RAR formats</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
    Support for the least commonly used archive formats from <c>unpack</c> has
    been removed:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>7-Zip (.7z)</li>
      <li>LHA (.lha, .lzh)</li>
      <li>RAR (.rar)</li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    Packages using these format for distfiles must now unpack them manually.
    Using <c>unpacker.eclass</c> is recommended for this.
    </p>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
