<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<devbook self="ebuild-writing/functions/src_prepare/eapply/">
<chapter>
<title>Patching with eapply</title>
<body>

<p>
The canonical way of applying patches in ebuilds is to use the package
manager's <c>eapply</c> command, either by calling it explicitly, or by
assigning the <c>PATCHES</c> variable supported by the default
<c>src_prepare</c> implementation.
</p>

<important>
Applying patches to the sources from the upstream tarball is <e>strongly</e>
preferred to distributing your own modified tarball.
</important>

<p>
The <c>eapply</c> command takes one or more regular file or directory paths as
its arguments. Optionally, these can be preceded by GNU <c>patch</c> options.
</p>

<note>
The <c>--</c> delimiter indicates the end of options. This is useful if a
filename begins with a hyphen.
</note>

<ul>
  <li>
    If an argument is a regular file, it will be applied in the working
    directory by calling GNU <c>patch</c> with patch level <c>-p1</c>.
    Specifying an explicit <c>-p<e>N</e></c> option will override the default
    patch level.
  </li>
  <li>
    For a directory, <c>eapply</c> applies all patch files with names ending
    in <c>.diff</c> or <c>.patch</c> in that directory, in POSIXbetical order
    of their names. Any other files in the directory are ignored.
    Again, <c>-p<e>N</e></c> can be used to override the default <c>-p1</c>
    patch level. Note that <c>eapply</c> will not recurse into subdirectories.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
<c>eapply</c> was added in EAPI 6. It differs from the previously available
<c>epatch</c> in several ways:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>eapply</c> will not unpack patches for you.
  </li>
  <li>
    The patch level is no longer detected automatically. Patch levels other
    than <c>-p1</c> must be specified manually.
  </li>
  <li>
    When specifying a directory, at least one file with a name ending in
    <c>.diff</c> or <c>.patch</c> must exist or the command fails.
  </li>
</ul>
</body>

<section>
<title>Basic <c>eapply</c></title>
<body>

<p>
In its simplest form, <c>eapply</c> takes a single filename and applies that
patch. It will automatically <c>die</c> if the apply fails. The following is
taken from <c>sys-libs/gpm</c>:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
	eapply "${FILESDIR}"/${P}-musl.patch
</codesample>

<p>
In the following simplified example taken from <c>www-client/firefox</c>,
a patchset is added to <c>SRC_URI</c> in order to fetch and unpack it.
<c>eapply</c> is then called with a directory argument. It applies all patches
found in that directory:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
SRC_URI+="https://dev.gentoo.org/~larry/patchsets/${P}-patches-01.tar.xz"

src_prepare() {
	eapply "${WORKDIR}/firefox-patches"
	eapply_user
}
</codesample>

<p>
The <uri link="::ebuild-writing/misc-files/patches/"/> chapter gives some
guidelines about where patches should be hosted and about their formatting.
</p>

<p>
The default <c><uri link="::ebuild-writing/functions/src_prepare/"/></c>
function will look for a global PATCHES array to apply a list of patches
for you.
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
PATCHES=(
	# Fix install location
	"${FILESDIR}/${P}-destdir.patch"
	# Respect MAKEOPTS #876543
	"${FILESDIR}/${P}-parallel_build.patch"
)
</codesample>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Advanced <c>eapply</c></title>
<body>

<p>
This example shows how different patch levels can be applied:
</p>

<codesample lang="ebuild">
src_prepare() {
	eapply -p2 "${WORKDIR}/${P}-suse-update.patch"
	eapply -p0 "${FILESDIR}/${PV}-no-TIOCGDEV.patch"
	eapply "${FILESDIR}/${PV}-gcc-6.patch"
	eapply_user
}
</codesample>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</devbook>
