<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="general-concepts/projects/">
<chapter>
<title>Projects</title>
<body>

<p>
The management structure of Gentoo, called the "metastructure", is
defined in
<uri link="https://www.gentoo.org/glep/glep-0039.html#specification">
GLEP 39</uri>. In Gentoo, a project is a group of developers working
towards a common goal in various different areas. For example, the
<uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Devmanual">
Devmanual</uri> project focuses on maintaining this document. Many
others are responsible for maintaining packages. Projects spanning a
large area of topics can have multiple subprojects specializing in
particular fields within the domain of the parent project and thus
form a project hierarchy.
</p>

<p>
A package maintained by a project needs to have the
project explicitly listed as a maintainer in its
<uri link="::ebuild-writing/misc-files/metadata/">metadata.xml</uri>.
The full listing of all the projects can be found on
<uri link="https://api.gentoo.org/metastructure/projects.xml">
api.gentoo.org</uri> or on the
<uri link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Gentoo">wiki</uri>.
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Starting new projects</title>
<body>

<p>
According to the metastructure any developer may create a new
project. There are two procedures involved in starting a new project:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Create a new project page <uri
    link="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Gentoo_Wiki:Developer_Central/Project_pages">
    through the wiki</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Post a Request For Comments (RFC) email to the gentoo-dev
    mailing list.
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
There is no approval required for the RFC and negative comments do not
block a developer from creating a project. Competing projects are
allowed to co-exist in Gentoo; existence of another project with
similar goals do not block another developer from starting a new
project with the same goals.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Joining and leaving a project</title>
<body>

<p>
Members of a project are managed through the project's page on the
Gentoo Wiki. Each page has a "Project" template in its source which
lists the members of the project. Simply modifying the list is
sufficient for adding or removing a developer. Note that different
projects have different requirements and procedures for recruiting
developers, which may require prior arrangements to be made before
modifying the member list. It is standard however to consult
the project lead.
</p>

<p>
If the project has an official IRC channel listed on its project page,
developers should join the channel if possible to facilitate
coordination and collaboration.
</p>

<p>
Developers should remember to add themselves to the alias by editing
<c>/var/mail/alias/misc/&lt;alias name&gt;</c> on
dev.gentoo.org. For example, the alias for the Devmanual project is
located at <c>/var/mail/alias/misc/devmanual</c>, which corresponds to
the project's email address <c>devmanual@gentoo.org</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
