<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide self="appendices/contributing/">
<chapter>
<title>Contributing to this document</title>

<body>
<p>
Contributions for this document are very welcome. Whether you've found a typo
or have written an entire new section, the best way to get in touch is via
Bugzilla. Please look at the
<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?product=Documentation;component=Devmanual;resolution=---">
bug list</uri> and file a
<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Documentation;component=Devmanual;format=guided">
new bug</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The editors reserve the right to modify submissions as they see fit. Any
substantial changes will of course be discussed with the submitter first <d/>
unless explicitly requested, minor typo corrections and formatting fixes will
not be discussed.
</p>

<p>
This document is licensed under the
<uri link="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</uri>.
If this is a problem, don't submit anything.
</p>

<p>
This document is produced using the DevBook XML build system. You can download
a snapshot of the system as well as the relevant XML files from Git,
see the <uri link="::appendices/contributing/#Where to find the sources">
following section</uri>. If you'd rather just work with plain text, that's
fine too <d/> the formatting can be easily done by someone else (meaning, us).
</p>
</body>

<section>
<title>Where to find the sources</title>
<body>

<p>
Currently, sources are hosted on
<uri link="https://gitweb.gentoo.org/proj/devmanual.git">git.gentoo.org</uri>.
For current Gentoo developers, access is at
<c>git+ssh://git@git.gentoo.org/proj/devmanual.git</c>.
Non-developers can clone the repository by typing
<c>git clone git://anongit.gentoo.org/proj/devmanual.git</c>.
The sources are also hosted on
<uri link="https://github.com/gentoo/devmanual">GitHub</uri>
for those who prefer to submit patches using pull requests.
</p>

<p>
To build the devmanual, simply run <c>make</c> in the top directory of
the repository. You need <c>xsltproc</c> (from <c>dev-libs/libxslt</c>)
for the XML to HTML conversion, <c>xmllint</c> (from <c>dev-libs/libxml2</c>)
for validation, and <c>rsvg-convert</c> (from <c>gnome-base/librsvg</c>) for
the SVG to PNG conversion used in some of the figures throughout the document.
</p>

<p>
To check if the document's XML is valid, run <c>make validate</c> in the
top-level directory, which will validate all XML files using <c>xmllint</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quick introduction to DevBook XML</title>
<body>

<p>
DevBook XML is heavily based on GuideXML and many tags are similar, if not
the same. The main differences occur in layout which are designed to make
a large-scale publication easier to produce and manage using a hierarchical
tree system. Before starting off you really should first examine the
<uri link="::appendices/devbook-guide/">DevBook XML guide</uri> in a reasonable
amount of depth.
</p>

</body>

<subsection>
<title>Differences from GuideXML</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>
    Indentation
  </dt>
  <dd>
    Indent when needed <d/> you should not indent any section flow elements
    such as <c>&lt;subsection&gt;</c> but do indent tables, lists and
    definition lists. Do <e>not</e> indent text in ordinary paragraph blocks.
  </dd>
  <dt>
    Code samples
  </dt>
  <dd>
    You can use the normal GuideXML tag <c>&lt;pre&gt;</c> when you need
    no syntax highlighting. When you need syntax highlighting use the
    <c>&lt;codesample&gt;</c> tag along with a <c>lang</c> attribute <d/>
    usually you want this to be set to <c>ebuild</c> to syntax highlight ebuild
    code snippets.
  </dd>
  <dt>
    Hierarchy
  </dt>
  <dd>
    The whole document is organized as a tree. Each directory can contain
    one document. Each document can inherit multiple sub-documents using the
    <c>&lt;include&gt;</c> flag. You <b>must</b> ensure that the <c>self</c>
    tag in each document correctly points to the relative path of the document
    from the root node so that the tree-walking algorithms work correctly.
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Style guidelines</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
  This document is in British English. Submissions in other kinds of English are
  welcome, but they may have their spelling corrected.
  </li>
  <li>
  Third person form should be used rather than first.
  </li>
  <li>
  This is not a formal document. The writing style is intended to be
  professional but readable.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
