<?xml version="1.0"?>
<guide self="appendices/contributing/">
<chapter>
<title>Contributing to This Document</title>

<body>
<p>
Contributions for this document are very welcome. Whether you've found a typo
or have written an entire new section, the best way to get in touch is via Bugzilla
at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The editors reserve the right to modify submissions as they see fit. Any
substantial changes will of course be discussed with the submitter first <d/>
unless explicitly requested, minor typo corrections and formatting fixes will
not be discussed.
</p>

<p>
This document is licensed under the <uri link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/">
Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 2.0 License </uri>. If this is a problem,
don't submit anything.
</p>

<p>
This document is produced using the DevBook XML build system. You can download
a snapshot of the system as well as the relevant XML files from Subversion. You
can also view the XML of any page by replacing <c>index.html</c> with
<c>text.xml</c> in the URL. If you'd rather just work with plain text, that's
fine too <d/> the formatting can be easily done by someone else (meaning, us).
</p>

<subsection>
  <title>Where to find the sources</title>
  <body>

<p>
  Currently, sources are hosted on git.overlays.gentoo.org. For current Gentoo developers,
  access is at <c>git+ssh://git@git.overlays.gentoo.org/proj/devmanual.git</c>. Non-developers
  can clone the respository by typing <c>git clone git://git.overlays.gentoo.org/proj/devmanual.git</c>.
</p>

<p>
  To build the devmanual, simply run <c>make</c> in the <c>trunk</c> directory of the repository.
  You need <c>xsltproc</c> (from <c>dev-libs/libxslt</c>) for the XML to HTML
  conversion and optionally also <c>ImageMagick</c> for the SVG to PNG conversion
  used in some of the figures throughout the document.
</p>
  </body>
</subsection>

</body>

<section>
<title>Quick Introduction to DevBook XML</title>
<body>

<p>
DevBook XML is heavily based on <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">
GuideXML</uri> and many tags are similar, if not the same. The main differences
occur in layout which are designed to make a large-scale publication easier
to produce and manage using a hierarchical tree system. Before starting off you
really should first examine the GuideXML guide in a reasonable amount of depth.
</p>

<subsection>
<title>Differences from GuideXML</title>
<body>

<dl>
  <dt>
    Indentation
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
      Indent when needed <d/> you should not indent any section flow elements such as
      <c>&lt;subsection&gt;</c> but do indent tables, lists and definition lists.
      Do <e>not</e> indent text in ordinary paragraph blocks.
    </p>
  </dd>
  <dt>
    Code Samples
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
      You can use the normal GuideXML tag <c>&lt;pre&gt;</c> when you need no syntax
      highlighting. When you need syntax highlighting use the <c>&lt;codesample&gt;</c>
      tag along with a <c>lang</c> attribute <d/> usually you want this to be set to
      <c>ebuild</c> to syntax highlight ebuild code snippets.
    </p>
  </dd>
  <dt>
    Hierarchy
  </dt>
  <dd>
    <p>
      The whole document is organized as a tree. Each directory can contain one
      document. Each document can inherit multiple sub-documents using the
      <c>&lt;include&gt;</c> flag. You <b>must</b> ensure that the <c>self</c> tag
      in each document correctly points to the relative path of the document from
      the root node so that the tree-walking algorithms work correctly.
    </p>
  </dd>
</dl>

</body>
</subsection>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Style Guidelines</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
  This document is in British English. Submissions in other kinds of English are
  welcome, but they may have their spelling corrected.
  </li>
  <li>
  Third person form should be used rather than first.
  </li>
  <li>
  This is not a formal document. The writing style is intended to be
  professional but readable.
  </li>
  <li>
  When using in-sentence hyphens as punctuation <d/> like this <d/> use a space,
  followed by the <c>&lt;d/&gt;</c> tag. The build system will automatically turn
  this into a proper Unicode long dash.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>

